<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Quakers vindicated from the calumnies of those that falsly accuse them as if they denyed magistrates, and disowned government; and as if both in principle and practice they were inconsistant with either. In which is shewed, that the true and sincere Quakers (so called, for of them I write) are in the spirit and principle in which the justice of magistrates is obeyed, and in which magistrates are to administer their government, and that by their practice in good works they fulfill all just and good government. And that they have God's authority for their meeting together to worship Him, ... And that people in matters of religion and the worship of God, should rather be instructed and led by the Spirit of the Lord in Gods authority, ... Also, several objections answered, as to the exercise of secular force and compulsion over the conscience in matters of faith, religion, and the worship of God. By Edward Pyot.</title>
            <author>Pyot, Edward, d. 1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4316A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25210</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834850</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834850</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39442</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70887)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39442)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1267:13, 2014:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Quakers vindicated from the calumnies of those that falsly accuse them as if they denyed magistrates, and disowned government; and as if both in principle and practice they were inconsistant with either. In which is shewed, that the true and sincere Quakers (so called, for of them I write) are in the spirit and principle in which the justice of magistrates is obeyed, and in which magistrates are to administer their government, and that by their practice in good works they fulfill all just and good government. And that they have God's authority for their meeting together to worship Him, ... And that people in matters of religion and the worship of God, should rather be instructed and led by the Spirit of the Lord in Gods authority, ... Also, several objections answered, as to the exercise of secular force and compulsion over the conscience in matters of faith, religion, and the worship of God. By Edward Pyot.</title>
                  <author>Pyot, Edward, d. 1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Item at 1267:13 has cropped imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library and the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39442:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39442:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The QUAKERS Vindicated from the Calumnies of thoſe that falſly accuſe them as if they <hi>Denyed</hi> MAGISTRATES, and <hi>Diſowned</hi> GOVERNMENT; And as if both in Principle and Practice they were inconſiſtant with either.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In which is ſhewed,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the true and ſincere <hi>Quakers</hi> (ſo called, for of them I write) are in the Spirit and Principle in which the Juſtice of Magiſtrates is obeyed, and in which Magiſtrates are to adminiſter their Government, and that by their practice in good works they fulfill all juſt and good Government.</p>
            <p>And that they have God's Authority for their meeting together to worſhip Him, and the Name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (which is above every name) to meet in; And that their Worſhip in Spirit is allowed by the Scriptures of Truth, and the practice of the Primitive Chriſtians, which was before either the <hi>Liturgie</hi> or the <hi>Maſſe-book</hi> was.</p>
            <p>And that people in the matters of Religion and the Worſhip of God, ſhould rather be inſtructed and led by the Spirit of the Lord in Gods Authority, than driven by the terrour of Magiſtrates, and forc'd by the penalties and puniſhments of the outward Laws of Men.</p>
            <p>Alſo, ſeveral <hi>Objections</hi> anſwered, as to the exerciſe of Secular force and compulſion over the Conſcience in matters of Faith, Religion, and the Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDWARD PYOT.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>But truly I am full of power by the Spirit of the Lord, and of judgment and of might, to declare unto Jacob his tranſgreſſions, and to Iſrael his ſin. Hear this, I pray you, ye Heads of the houſe of Jacob, and Princes of the houſe of Iſrael, that abhor Judgment, and pervert all Equity; they build up Zion with blood, and Jeruſalem with iniquity.</hi> 
               <bibl>Mich. 3. 8, 9, 10.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Knowing this, that the Law is not made for a righteous man, but for the lawleſs and diſobedient, for the ungodly and for ſinners, for the unholy and prophane, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <bibl>1 Tim. 1. 9, 10.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:39442:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:39442:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>vindicated from the Calumnies of thoſe that falſly accuſe them as if they denyed Magiſtrates, and diſowned Government,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IT is no ſtrange thing if there be a talk among ſome people, that the <hi>Quakers</hi> (ſo called) do deny Magiſtrates and diſown Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for ſuch there were in the times of Chriſt and of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who, of malice ſome, and others of ignorance, ſlandered both Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and the moſt ſincere Chriſtians of all Ages ſince, with ſuch falſe accuſations and ſcandalous reports: it was through envy and ſlander that Chriſt was by the <hi>Jews</hi> delivered as a Malefactor in this kind, as <hi>Pilate</hi> well knew, whom the chief Prieſt, the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ders and Scribes, with their multitude, accuſed of perverting the Nations, and forbidding to pay Tribute to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and of ſtirring up the people; and this they did under pretence of friendſhip to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> who in their hearts they hated; they told <hi>Pilate</hi> that he was not <hi>Caeſar's</hi> friend if he let him go, when he ſought to releaſe him, as finding no fault in him, and cryed for <hi>Barrabas</hi> to be releaſed, who did indeed prevert the people, and made Inſurrection, and committed Murder in the Inſurrection, and for Sedition and Murther was caſt into Priſon. And they laid in many great &amp; grievious complaints againſt the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as touching the Law of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and of moving Sedition, and of turning the world upſide down; and they accuſed them of doing contrary to the Decrees of <hi>Ceſar.</hi> And the Chriſtians in after-times were ſaid to be ſeditious and rebellious, and pernicious to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; and whatſoever evils happened among the people, they were imputed to the Chriſtians as the cauſers thereof. Thus the moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtians of their times, have been ſcandalized, defamed, and perſecuted, by the malice of them, who through their ſubtilty and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie to Righteouſneſs, have endeavoured by all ways and means to bring the moſt Innocent and upright People into contempt with their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and to poſſeſs the ignorant people with prejudice againſt them; that having rendred them infamous and dangerous, they might be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted as ſuch: and as ſuch, many have unjuſtly ſuffered by their Rulers, and by the miſ-led people have been diſregarded and had in baſe eſteem, and accounted as the filth of the world, and as the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of all things.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is no ſtrange thing, if the moſt ſincere Chriſtians
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39442:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of theſe times, that are now reproachfully called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and <hi>Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and their Miniſters <hi>Ringleaders,</hi> (as the Chriſtians in the Apoſtles times were called <hi>Nazarens,</hi> and termed <hi>a Sect,</hi> and their Miniſters <hi>Ringleaders)</hi> be now ſlandered and defamed, as if they denyed Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and diſowned Government, and were in their principle and practice inconſiſtent with both, by the ſcandalous reports of ſome, who through their envy to Godlineſs and Sincerity, have evilly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and hatched ſuch things, without any cauſe given, whereby the Rulers alſo have been incenſed againſt the Innocent, as a People diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to Government.</p>
            <p>And this ſubtile and malicious working was in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s dayes as well as now, and hath been through all the late Changes; although the <hi>Quakers</hi> never gave occaſion to any, yet occaſions have been taken againſt them by all, and they have been made offenders, and have deeply ſuffered by all, who never juſtly offended any, nor are in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple or practice prejudicial to either Government or Governours, but are for the eſtabliſhment of both, according to the Ordinance of God; and by their honeſt converſation (which is according to the will of God in well-doing, which well becometh good Government) they do anſwer the end of Government; and their Principle teacheth them, according to the will of God, to ſubmit themſelves to every Ordinance of man, for the Lord's ſake; and they know it to be the will of God corcerning them, that they may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men, according as <hi>Peter</hi> writeth to the Chriſtians that were ſcattered abroad in ſeveral parts, <hi>That they ſhould be of honeſt converſation among the Gentiles, and ſubmit themſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether to the King as Supream, or unto Governors, as unto them that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">61. 2.</note> 
               <hi>are ſent of him, for the puniſhment of evil-doors, and for the praiſe of them that do well;</hi> and that this to do, was the will of God concerning them, <hi>that with well-doing they might put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if well-doing (which indeed is an honour to Government, and not a diſowning of it, and which deſerves the Magiſtrates praiſe, and therefore is no denying them) was a ſufficient ground to put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men in this matter, as to the Chriſtians in the Apoſtles times; why may not the well-doing of the <hi>Quakers</hi> now (who as to their honeſt converſation, innocent life and quiet behaviour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards both Rulers and People, have a large teſtimony in the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of all that know them) be a ſufficient ground to put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men, as to this matter, in this our day? And thoſe who ſo bewray their ignorance, as thus to talk, may not unfitly be termed <hi>fooliſh men:</hi> for what reaſon is there for juſt and righteous
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39442:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
men to diſown Government, that to ſay, juſt and righteous Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that are ſo obedient to the Government of God's Spirit ruling in them, (which Spirit of God is to govern Governours in their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments) as that their converſation is ſo according to good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as that good Government hath no Law againſt them?</p>
            <p>What reaſon is there for people that are ſubject to the Government of God, to be againſt the Government of men, if they rule according to God, whoſe Kingdom is to rule over all, and that adminiſter their Government for the Lords ſake, for the puniſhment of evil-doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well? for although unrighteous Rulers, who know not the Lord to rule over them and by them, nor are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to his Power in their Governments, by their corrupt rule and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government, and abuſe of their Power, do perſecute the Innocent, that obey the Government of God, for their Righteouſneſs ſake; yet the Government of men, by the Ordinance of God, is not to puſh againſt the Government of God in his People, that are of his own Houſhold and Family, and under his own Government, in whom his Kingdom is come, and his Will is done; who know the Lord to be their Ruler, and are ſubject unto his Power and Rule in them and over them, and obey him as their King, their Lawgiver and Judge, who by their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Reign and Government of God, do anſwer and fulfil the juſt and good Government of men? and therefore there is no reaſon for the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who are under the Government of God, to be againſt the Government of men, that rule according to the Ordinance of God.</p>
            <p>Again, Rulers are not to be a terror to good works, but their Sword is to be turned againſt the evil, and they are to miniſter their good to well-doers; and therefore thoſe who are redeemed from their evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds, which the Power of God in Rulers is God's Sword to puniſh, they need not to fear the Power, the occaſion of the Sword being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued in them by the Power of their Redeemer: but the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> are redeemed from the evil deeds, which the Sword of the Magiſtrate is to puniſh, ſo that they are not chargeable by any, to be converſant therein; for, they having renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſty, are not found in criminal offences; nor are they by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>obereſt of men, charged with any ungodly or vicious living, to which the Magiſtrate is to be a terrour; And therefore the <hi>Quakers</hi> need not to fear the Power, which to Magiſtrates is given by God, for the puniſhment of evil-doers only, and not to puniſh well-doers, the occaſion of the Sword being ſubdued in them by the Power of their Redeemer, who breaks in pieces (and hath broken in them) the power
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39442:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and rule of darkneſs, which keeps in tranſgreſſion, and ſubdues the tranſgreſſor, and keeps out of tranſgreſſion; unto whoſe Power in them (which is the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> in which Rulers are to govern, that over-rules and rules over the power and rule of darkneſs, and that chains down the evil-doer and reſtrains his evil deeds) their ſouls are ſubject.</p>
            <p>Again. Rulers, by the Ordinance of God, are to miniſter their good to well-doers; and therefore thoſe who are in the exerciſe of good-works, by the power of their Head <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> working in them, (who is the Head of all Principalitie and Power; of whom alone is all the juſt Authority and Rule that is derived unto the Rulers of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by whoſe Power Rulers are to govern) his Power in their Governments, is for their praiſe, who by his Power in them are exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in good-works, which good-works are the fulfilling of good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and unto which good Governours are a praiſe: But the <hi>Quakers</hi> are a People that are exerciſed in good works, by the power of their Head <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> working in them, ſo as that they are an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of good works at this day in the Nation, the proof of which they have in the conſciences of all ſober People; and therefore Magiſtrates are to miniſter their good unto the <hi>Quakers</hi> as unto well-doers, and to protect and encourage them in their well-doing: For the Power of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as it rules in Government, is for their praiſe, who by his, Power in them are exerciſed in good works; which good works are the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of good Government, and unto which good Governours are a praiſe, as it is written, <hi>Wilt thou then not be afraid of the Power? do</hi> 
               <note place="margin">13.</note> 
               <hi>that which is good, and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame: for he is the Miniſter of God to thee for good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe who (in the Divine and Spiritual Light of their Creator) are ſubject to the righteous Law of their Maker, which in their hearts is written from their creation, the Law of the Creation, which from the beginning hath been given by God, in common to all Nations (before the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>Jews</hi> was given) the Creators Law to his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and as their Sovereign Lord, over all Sovereignty and Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, his Law, for the government of the Creation, and ſo the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law of all Nations, according to which the Nations by their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are to be governed, as the Jews by their Rulers were to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned according to the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> theſe, by their obedience to the righteous Law of God, they obey the righteous Laws of men, for conſcience-ſake, and ſubmit to every Ordinance of man for the Lord's ſake; and ſo their obedience to the Laws of men, and their ſubmiſſion to every Ordinance of man, is without the force of the Law, or the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39442:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
wrath of man, for which they merit of the Magiſtrate his praiſe, and the Laws protection, for their encouragement in their wel-doing.</p>
            <p>For in the Law of God is contained the true principles of all Law and Juſtice, that by Rulers in their Governments is to be adminiſtred; and every Ordinance of man, <hi>viz.</hi> the Magiſtracy and Government of every Nation is to be compoſed and conſtituted, according to the Law of God, and by the Law of God, as their principle, and their inward guide, their Laws, their Judgments and Sentences are to be directed and regulated; And therefore thoſe, who are ſubject to the righteous Law of God, (the record of which is written in their hearts) they keep the Laws of men, and every Ordinance of man, that is according to the Law of God and his Ordinance: for the Laws of men are not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from the Law of God, nor is any Ordinance of man, ſo to be of man, as not to be of God; for the motive to ſubmit to every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man, is, <hi>for the Lord's ſake;</hi> and therefore every Ordinance of man, in their original, muſt be of God, and of man only formally, as by man compoſed and conſtituted; And as every Ordinance is of man, ſo every Ordinance muſt by man be ordained for the Lords ſake, that ſo every Ordinance of man may be ſubmitted unto for the Lord's ſake, (as it is written) <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13, 14. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King, as Supream; or unto Governours, as unto them that are ſent by him, for the puniſhment of evil-doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thoſe who are ſubject to the Power of God, as the Power of God reigns in their ſouls, and bears rule over their whole man, (which Power of God is the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> unto which every ſoul is to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as well the Rulers in their Rule, as the Ruled in their Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) they muſt needs be ſubject to the Government of the ſame Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God, as it reigns in the ſouls of their Rulers, and as it bears the Rule in their Governments: for the Power of God, which is to reign and rule in every mans own particular, is the ſame which is to reign and rule in the Governments of men; elſe how are they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in themſelves who reſiſt the Power as it rules in Government, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 2. It is the reign of the Power to condemnation in them that reſiſt, that condemns them for their reſiſting the Rule of the Power as it reigns in Government; And therefore thoſe that are ſubject to the reign of the Power of God, as it rules in themſelves, they muſt needs be ſubject to the Rule of the Power of God as it reigns in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments of men.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Quakers</hi> are ſubject to the Power of God, and in their ſouls the Power of God reigns, and bears the rule over their whole man;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39442:5"/>
and therefore the <hi>Quakers</hi> muſt needs be ſubject, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience-ſake they are ſubject to the Governments of the ſame Power of God, as it reigns in their Rulers, and as it rules in their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; neither dare they reſiſt the Power of God in their Rulers, leſt the Power of God in themſelves be their condemnation.</p>
            <p>But rather, that by the Regal Reign and Rule of the Power of God in themſelves, they may be ſo regulated, and their wayes ſo bounded unto the Lord, as that within the limits of the Power they may be preſerved to anſwer the ſame in their Rulers; and their converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the fear of God ſo ordered, and by his Wiſdom and in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel ſo directed and governed, that as the ſame rules and guides in their Rulers, they be found regular with all juſt and good Government; and that in the Dominion of the ſame Power of God reigning in them, by which Kings reign, themſelves in the Power may reign, as Kings on Earth, over all unrighteouſneſs; And that by the Sovereign Conduct of the ſame Wiſdom of God, dictating and preſcribing to them, by which Princes decree Juſtice, they may be led in the wayes of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and guided in the midſt of the paths of Judgment, and the glorious Lord be unto them a place of broad Rivers and Streams, and their Judge their Lawgiver and their King.</p>
            <p>And ſo they being ſubject to the Power of God in themſelves, how can they reſiſt its rule in their Rulers? And their converſations being guided by the Counſel of God in themſelves, how can they tranſgreſs its conduct in Governments? Nay, but when Government is reduced to its true principle and firſt foundation, and as Governours are reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to their juſt and primitive Judicature, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 26. &amp; 60. 17. that <hi>Judgment returns to Righteouſneſs</hi> as its principle, (the Principle of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which is of God, the gift of God, in which Judgement is to be <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4. 85. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> executed) <hi>when Mercy and Truth meet, and Righteouſneſs and Peace kiſſe each other. For Righteouſneſs ſhall look down from Heaven, and Truth ſpring out of the Earth; and Judgment run down as Waters, and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs as a mighty Stream;</hi> And when the Power of God only ſhal be the ſtrength of Rulers, and the Authority and Ability of their Rule, and God's Wiſdom their Guide, and his Juſtice their Principle in their Governments and adminiſtration of their Laws, and Gods Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with them their Confidence and the ſtability of their times, and not the Arm of fleſh and Force of man, nor ſenſual ſubtilty and craft; I ſay, when theſe things are accompliſhed, and God's Promiſes ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled as to the Governments both of Nations and Families; And the day haſtneth in which Iniquity ſhall have an end: for the Lord hath overturned, and is overturning, and will overturn, until he come
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39442:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
whoſe right it is (and his day is begun, in which he rules in the midſt of his Enemies, and will wound the heads over many Countries, who <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Eccl</hi> 36. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> in their hearts ſay, <hi>There is none other but we)</hi> though darkned to many by the clouds in which he comes. And then the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as in their own conſciences they are now clear in the ſight of God as to their owning of Magiſtrates, and ſubmitting to their Governments in what righteouſly they can; ſo then ſhall they ſtand juſtified in the ſight of men, yea even in the conſciences of their greateſt enemies.</p>
            <p>And what can they now be accuſed of, even in theſe times of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and Apoſtacy, and the now hour and power of Darkneſs, in which the Sea roars and the waves thereof are let looſe in upon them, and the foundations of the Earth as it were moved becauſe of them; and if but five or more beſides the houſhold do meet in their own hired houſe to worſhip God, the third ſtep in this path is Baniſhment; and ſo to worſhip God out of the form of their <hi>Liturgy,</hi> though it be in Spirit and in Truth, is by this Generation made a Crime, and worthy of Baniſhment, if the number of five or above, as aforeſaid, do meet? for, if they do but ſay, <hi>they met together to worſhip God,</hi> it is evidence enough to the Court, ſaith the Judge, for the Jury to bring them in guilty, in order to their Sentence for Baniſhment. May not the wiſe in heart hear and perceive at what they ſtrike, and what ſtrikes? and <hi>Solomons</hi> prophetick ſight fulfilled, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Moreover, I ſaw under the Sun the place of Judgment, that wickedneſs was there: and the place of Righteouſneſs, that Iniquity was there?</hi> And but a few years ſince, the publick uſe of the <hi>Liturgy</hi> in Worſhip, was accounted diſobedience to Magiſtrates, and was cryed againſt in the Pulpits.</p>
            <p>But though they have no helper on earth, and the Power great that is riſen up againſt them; as <hi>Solomon</hi> beheld the tears of them that were oppreſſed, and they had no comforter; <hi>On the ſide of the Oppreſſer there was power, but they had no comforter,</hi> Eccl. 4. 1. yet the Lord is with them, and is their ſtrength; yea, and their inward conſolation, and exceeding great reward in all their tribulations. And is it not God's Preſence with them, the power and purity of his Appearance among them, that makes the workers of Iniquity afraid, and the Devil of his Kingdom: for, are not Meetings by fours privately, and with their doors ſhut, greater opportunities to contrive Inſurrections, if that only were the matter and alſo the intent of their Meetings, than the publick Aſſemblies of the <hi>Quakers</hi> with their doors open? and experience hath ſufficiently ſhewed that the <hi>Quakers</hi> are no Plotters, except againſt the Devil and his wiles and devices; nor is their war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare againſt fleſh and blood, for their weapons are ſpiritual.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:39442:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
I ſay, what can be laid to their charge, except in the matters of the Law of their God, and what relates to his Worſhip and Service? And in the oppoſite Commandments of God and men, muſt not God by them be obeyed rather than men? for, is there any power or admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Law to be ſubmitted unto againſt the Lord? And ſhall man preſcribe to God his Worſhip, who ſhould not preſcribe his own but by God's permiſſion? Is not this to oppoſe their power to the Power of God? and to ſet their Judgment-ſeats above the Throne of God? For, are Magiſtrates the Governours of the immortal Souls of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous? have they power over the Spirit? for, the Worſhip of God is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 24.</note> in Spirit.</p>
            <p>Do not they intrench on God's Prerogative, and uſurp in his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, who in the matters of Religion and materials of God's Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, do intrude outward and worldly Domination over the inward and Spiritual man? For, is the Spiritual man which judgeth all things, and is himſelf judged of no man, the Kingdom and Regiment of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Powers? and is the Soul their Judgment-ſeat? are they the Lords over Conſcience? have they the Dominion over the things of God, which by Chriſt are diſtinguiſhed from the things of <hi>Caeſar? Mat.</hi> 22. 21. Will they give Law to that in man which is not of man, and which they can neither protect nor puniſh, and from which in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves their Laws ſhould be given? For, is <hi>the hidden man of the heart</hi> puniſhable by man, which is not corruptible by the Devil? or, can they either ſave or kill the Soul? or, can they protect them from the Wrath of God, who to ſave themſelves from the wrath of man, do in the things of God fear and hearken unto man more than unto God?</p>
            <p>And in the matters of Religion and the Worſhip of God, are not people rather to be taught and led by the Spirit of God in God's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, than to be driven by the power of Magiſtrates, and forced by the penalties and puniſhments of outward Laws? And is that Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip acceptable to God, which for its authority hath only the force and fear of man, without the faith and fear of God? Is it the outward worſhip of the bodily preſence and exerciſe only, that is ſo well-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God? for neither doth the force of man reach further than to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k.</hi> 12</note> the outward body, <hi>nor can the wrath of man work the Righteouſneſs of God;</hi> or rather, is it not the inward and ſpiritual Worſhip in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Faith and renewed Spirit of God's faithful and true Worſhippers, that pleaſeth God? If the former, why then was not <hi>Cains</hi> Sacrifice accepted? and if the latter, how then can the Laws of men, and their moſt ſevere executions, make any to worſhip God acceptably; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by all their force they cannot give men Faith, nor make new
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39442:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their Spirit; for Faith is the gift of God, and to renew a right Spirit in man is the work of God; And <hi>without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> Heb. 11. 6. for, <hi>whatſoever is not of Faith is ſin,</hi> Rom. 14. 13. And it was <hi>by Faith that Abel offered a more acceptable ſacrifice than Cain,</hi> Heb. 11. 4.</p>
            <p>And how can they whoſe Conſciences are tender, and not ſeared as with an <hi>hot Iron,</hi> but be condemned in themſelves, if by the force and fear of men and their penalties and puniſhments, they worſhip God in the way preſcribed by man; that is contrary to their Faith, and againſt the judgment and feeling of their own Conſciences, and for which there is neither precept nor example in the Scriptures of Truth? <hi>And if their own hearts and conſciences condemn them, God is greater,</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 20. And ſo by the exerciſe of Force and Puniſhment in Religion and Worſhip, are there not many made Hypocrites? and are there not ſome made Hereticks? For, they are Hypocrites which appear to be that outwardly which they are not inwardly; and they are Hereticks who by ſubverſion, ſin, and are condemned in themſelvs; ſo that their obedience is not for Conſcience-ſake, but for Wraths-ſake only: And alſo by Force impoſing things contrary to Faith and Conſcience. Are not many driven out from amongſt them who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not touch any unclean thing? And when the Lord hath received them, are they not then perſecuted as Schiſmaticks and ſeditious Sectories?</p>
            <p>And, are themſelves in the <hi>Faith which worketh by Love,</hi> and which ſtands not in the wiſdom and ſtrength of men, but in the power and operation of God, who by miſchievous Stratagems and the Force of men would wrack the Faith of others, break their Peace, and wound their Conſciences; who in their own hearts have the anſwer of a good Conſcience in what they do, and are in the Peace which paſſeth the underſtanding of them that hate and perſecute them, and are built up in the moſt holy Faith, by which the Juſt live? for their Meetings are in the ſingleneſs of their hearts; and not <hi>under pretence</hi> as ſeditious Conventicles, but in <hi>all ſimplicity and godly ſincerity</hi> to worſhip God.</p>
            <p>And is <hi>not to perſecute for righteouſneſs-ſake, Cains</hi> way? for, was not <hi>Cain</hi> the firſt Perſecuter? and was not <hi>Cain</hi> of that wicked one, when in his wroth he ſlew his Brother, becauſe his own works were <hi>evil</hi> and his Brother's <hi>righteous?</hi> And are <hi>Revilings, Menacings, Striking, Stocking, Impriſoning</hi> and <hi>Baniſhing the Righteous for their Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs-ſake,</hi> are theſe the fruits of true and ſincere Chriſtians, and the fulfilling of the Law of Love? or, are theſe Cruelties of the Lord? for <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſteps of a good man are ordered by the Lord,</hi> and that <hi>he delighteth in his way.</hi> Are theſe ſteps ordered by the Lord? or, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:39442:7"/>
doth the Lord delight in this way? And if the Devil be the original author of theſe immanities, are not then raging foming Perſecuters, who travel with envy and miſchief, the Devil's Agents, and the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners of his Wrath and Cruelties upon the Innocent? for, it is written, <hi>Fear none of thoſe things that thou ſhalt ſuffer; Behold, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſhall caſt ſome of you into Priſon, that ye may be tryed.</hi> And Satan dwelt and had his ſeat, where <hi>Antipas</hi> God's faithful Martyr was ſlain; <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 10. 13.</p>
            <p>And, is the Lord their ſtrength, and his Arm and Protection their truſt and confidence, who cannot truſt a poor naked and harmleſs people to meet together to worſhip God, without ſuſpition of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Inſurrections? when no cauſe was ever given by the <hi>Quakers</hi> to ſuſpect them; but only as by machination they are rendred as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and ſeditious Sectaries, and diſloyal perſons; who indeed are but as Lambs among Wolves, and a prey to the beaſts of the field, and do not reſiſt the evil and the wrong that is done unto them, nor retalliate like for like; <hi>not being overcome of evil, but overcoming evil with good:</hi> Nor is it their principle to plot and contrive Inſurrections, but patiently to bear their falſe Calumnies, and chearfully to ſuffer their cruel Oppreſſions; and are not aſhamed of the Commandments of God, to do his will, nor of the Teſtimony of Chriſt for which they ſuffer; but by the Power of God are made willing to partake of the Affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions of the Goſpel; and do glory in their Tribulations, not lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their lives to the death; And loving their Enemies, and praying for their Perſecuters, they commit the keeping of their Souls unto him, who in his Faith and Patience is able to keep them throughout unto Himſelf, in this their day of tryal and hour of temptation that by the fierce and ſore wrath of man is come upon them.</p>
            <p>And, is it not as dangerous, and more diſloyalty to God, for any to defame and judge Gods true Worſhippers as ſeditious Sectaries who in the Spirit and in the Truth do worſhip God; and God's ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and holy Worſhip into which by the Spirit of God they are led, to be ſeditious Conventicles; who is a Spirit, and the Truth, and therefore muſt be worſhipped in Spirit and in Truth; and ſuch ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and true Worſhippers the Father ſeeks to worſhip him, <hi>John</hi> 4. 23, 24. For, is not this to defame and to judge the holy Spirit of God, by which God's true Worſhipers are led, and in which they holily and ſpiritually do worſhip God, to be <hi>ſeditious,</hi> and his holy and ſpiritual Worſhip, to be <hi>Sedition?</hi> for is it not written, <hi>He that speaketh evil of his Brother, and judgeth his Brother, ſpeaketh evil of the Law, and judgeth the Law: but if thou judge the Law, thou art not a doer of the Law, but</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:39442:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Are Chriſtians to be each others Judges in the matters of Faith and Religion? or, are they to be Maſters over the Conſciences one of another concerning the Worſhip of God? Is not the Lord himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone both the Lawgiver and Judge, as to his own Spiritual Worſhip and Service? for, is it not written, <hi>There is one Lawgiver, who is able to ſave, and to deſtroy? Who art thou that judgeſt another?</hi> Jam. 4. 12. And if God only be the Lawgiver and Judge, as to his own Worſhip and Service; is it then in the power of any living upon the face of the Earth, to preſcribe to God his Worſhip? or for the Worſhip of God with man's judgement to judge his true Worſhippers? And do not they preſcribe, who by their Laws and Penalties do bind and limit to a form of Worſhip not preſcribed or limited unto by God; nor in the practice of the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians? And do not they judge, who arraign and ſentence, even to Priſons and Baniſhment, them that for Conſcience-ſake cannot ſubmit to what by men is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for the Worſhip of God?</p>
            <p>And are not their Meetings of the Lord, and ſealed in them to be well-pleaſing in his ſight, by his Preſence with them and his Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in them and among them? for, are not the manifeſtations of his Spirit, and the operations of his Power in their holy Aſſemblies, a ſure Teſtimony from God of his acceptance of them in his Service and Worſhip? And have they not then God's Authority for their meeting together in his Name, the only Lord of their Conſciences, and the only Lawgiver for his own Worſhip and Service?</p>
            <p>And muſt Magiſtrates in the things of the outward man, by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians be obeyed for Conſcience-ſake in things not againſt Conſcience? And muſt not the Lord himſelf by his People be obeyed for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence-ſake in the things of the inward man? And muſt every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man be ſubmitted unto for the Lord's ſake, that is not againſt the Lord? and muſt not the Lord himſelf be ſubmitted unto for his own ſake, by his true Worſhippers in his own worſhip and Service?</p>
            <p>And, is not this to domineer and rule over, and over-rule the Faith and Conſciences of God's true Worſhippers (which by both <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in words is diſclaimed, which condemns their deeds) to impoſe upon them in the Worſhip of God, not only contrary to what in the ſight of God is made manifeſt in their Conſciences for the VVorſhip of God, and which is according to the VVord of Truth, and as by the Spirit of Chriſt in their hearts is preſcribed to them, but alſo in other manner than by the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians God was worſhipped, before either the Common-Prayer Book or the Maſs-Book was? whoſe manner of VVorſhip was then ſaid to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39442:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to Law, and by them called <hi>Hereſie,</hi> who reputed their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law; as it fares at this day with the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who after the manner which is now called <hi>Hereſie,</hi> by them who are themſelves in the Hereſie, they, as the Apoſtles did, do worſhip God, even their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the Spirit and in the Truth.</p>
            <p>And if the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians did meet together <hi>above the number of Four beſides the houſhold,</hi> and in their Meeting <hi>did worſhip God in other manner than is allowed by the Liturgy or practice of the Church of England,</hi> before the <hi>Liturgy</hi> was; why ſhould it be made an unlawful meeting now, and ſo capital as to be ſo ſeverely puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as with Baniſhment, for the <hi>Quakers</hi> to meet together before the Lord, above the number of Four beſides the houſhold, and in their meeting to worſhip God, in that manner in which God may be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, otherwiſe than is allowed by the Liturgy or practice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and as by the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians God was worſhipped before the <hi>Liturgy</hi> was, to wit, in the Spirit and in the Truth, as they did, ſeeing they are of the ſame Faith, and in the ſame Spirit and Truth, and under the ſame obligation as to their Conſciences as they were?</p>
            <p>And by Chriſt are purchaſed into the ſame Liberty, for the free ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Faith and Conſciences towards God, in his own Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and one towards another in the Truth and Service of <hi>God</hi> and one another in the <hi>Lord;</hi> which Liberty, freely to exerciſe their Faith and Conſciences in the <hi>Worſhip of God,</hi> they may no more part with in vaſſalage to man, than with their Lives: for in the Liberty and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of their Faith and Conſciences, in which Chriſt hath made them free, are they not to ſtand faſt to <hi>God alone,</hi> whoſe Servants they are, and the only Lord and Maſter of their Faith and Conſciences, and not again to be entangled with the Yokes of Bondage? leſt by captivating the Faith and defiling their Conſciences, they ſo become the ſervants of men, as not becoming the Servants of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And if any, notwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hſtanding what hath been ſaid, do yet aſſert, <hi>That the Worſhip preſcribed in the Liturgy is the only and true Worſhip of God, and that God can no otherwiſe be truly and ſpiritually worſhipped but as is preſcribed and allowed by the Liturgy or practice of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> do they not conſequently conclude the Worſhip of the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians to be falſe, who worſhipped not by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> but in Spirit before the <hi>Liturgy</hi> was? And did not Chriſt to the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſay, <hi>The hour cometh, and now is,</hi> 4. (this was before the <hi>Liturgy) when the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and in Truth, and that the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:39442:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>him?</hi> May it not therefore rather be aſſerted, That God may be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe worſhipped than by the preſcript of the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> or then is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the practice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to wit, in Spirit and in Truth, which by Chriſt is preſcribed for the Worſhip of God, and by the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians was practiſed, before the <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> was; which Worſhip in the Spirit and in the Truth, not only ended the Temple-worſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but alſo is repugnant to all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented worſhips of every Nation.</p>
            <p>And if it be ſaid by any, (as in effect it hath been ſaid by ſome, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed wiſe and learned, to juſtifie the uſe of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> or <hi>Liturgie,</hi> as they call it) <hi>That there is no Form of Worſhip pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſely declared and preſcribed by God for his Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, If there be no Form of Worſhip declared and preſcribed by God; ſhould not men then tremble to preſcribe where God hath not preſcribed? and muſt that therefore be the Worſhip of God which is preſcribed by men? And if they find not preciſely declared and preſcribed the Form of God's Worſhip in the Scripture, doth it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow that the Form of God's Worſhip is not preciſely declared and preſcribed by God? or that which may be thought to be omitted by God, that it muſt therefore be ſupplyed by man? Doth God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely require his Worſhip? and doth he not as preciſely preſcribe the Form how he will be worſhipped, to them of whom he requires it? Was <hi>Moſes</hi> faithful in all his houſe as a Servant? and is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> as a Son over his own houſe? for, is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> the King and Prophet of his Church? and is this only titular, or an idle dignity, without fruit or effectual operation and vertue? for, as their King and Prophet, is not <hi>Christ</hi> ever preſent with his, by his Spirit that dwelleth in them, and that abideth with them for ever, to teach them and to lead them, and to guide and govern them? for, did not <hi>Chriſt</hi> before he was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, tell his Diſciples that he would not leave them as Orphans, but that he would come to them again, and manifeſt himſelf unto them, and with the Father make his abode with them? And is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> alſo in the boſom of the Father, to make known his will concerning his own Worſhip and Service? And do not his Sheep hear and know his Voice, and learn of him? and doth he not ſhew them plainly of the Father, as it is written, <hi>The time cometh when I ſhall no more ſpeak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in Parables, but I ſhall ſhew you plainly of the Father?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Is not the manner and form of God's Worſhip, preciſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and preſcribed by God in the Scriptures, to be <hi>in Spirit and in Truth?</hi> and if that be doubtful, or hidden and unknown to them which are eſteemed wiſe and learned, which in the Scripture is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39442:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true Worſhippers ſhall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>the Father in Spirit and in Truth?</hi> And if theſe be enigmatical ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>viz, To them that have eyes, and ſee but perceive not; and have ears and hear, but underſtand not. God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth;</hi> Yet herein, is there not a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hn</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> plain deſcription by <hi>Chriſt</hi> of the Worſhip of God, to them that are taught of God, and have the mind of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and by the Spirit of Truth are led and guided into all Truth? And wherein any thing which <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpake to his Diſciples, whilſt he was preſent with them in the body, was at all obſcure and ambiguous to them, becauſe of their weakneſs; did not <hi>Chriſt</hi> direct them to the Teachings of the holy Spirit as to all things and for the bringing all things to their remembrance, and opening their underſtandings in all whatſoever he had ſaid unto them? And what then, in the Worſhip of God, is there more preciſe, which hath not been preſcribed and declared at firſt by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and which ſince hath not been, or may not in all the parts of God's Worſhip be plainly deſcribed by the holy Ghoſt, in the hearts and conſciences of God's faithful and true Worſhippers, whom the Father ſeeketh to worſhip him; although perhaps it may be hidden from them, who reject the Counſel of God within themſelves, and deſpiſe the moſt ſure Conduct of his Spirit, who leads into all Truth, and who chuſe to themſelves the Worſhip which is after the Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Commandments of men?</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as God may be worſhipped in other manner, than is allowed by the Liturgy or practice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as by the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians he was before the Liturgy was; and as by <hi>Chriſt</hi> is preſcribed for the Worſhip of God, to wit, <hi>in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and in Truth;</hi> why ſhould endeavours be uſed with ſuch extremity againſt a People that fear the Lord, whoſe conſciences are tender and ſenſible, and in the feeling of that which offends the Lord, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to obſtruct them in their juſt-Liberty, purchaſed to them as <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the free exerciſe of their Faith and Conſciences, to worſhip God in that manner in which God may be worſhipped, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than is allowed by the Liturgy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but alſo by their Laws to limit them to another manner of Worſhip, than that in which God may be worſhipped; and otherwiſe than that into which they by the Spirit of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are led to worſhip God; and other than that which by the primitive Chriſtians was practiſed for the Worſhip of God; and which they no where find in the Scriptures either limited unto or preſcribed; and which the Witneſs of God in their Conſciences is againſt?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:39442:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Do not the ſtronger herein (by their ſtrength) rule over the weak, in the things of God, which by <hi>Chriſt</hi> are diſtinguiſhed from the things that are <hi>Caeſars?</hi> Is not this by might and by power, to over-rule the Heritage of God, againſt their knowledge of the will of God, and what God requires of them? and againſt the divine wiſdom, and their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual underſtanding, which God hath given them for his Service and Worſhip? and againſt their faith, and what they really believe to be the true and ſpiritual Worſhip of God? and againſt the diſcerning and judgment, which by the gift of God is ſeated in their hearts and ſouls; by which they diſtinguiſh in themſelves, and do judge rightly of things that differ, and approve of that which is moſt excellent; and which is acceptable and well-pleaſing in the ſight of God, yea and againſt the witneſs of God in them, and the feeling of their own conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; And is not to rule by force the Lambs of Chriſt, and to give law and rule to their faith and conſciences, by penalties and puniſhments, contrary to what is written <hi>Zech.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>Not by Might, nor by Power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts?</hi> Is the ſtrength of men then, and their Force and Laws, Penalties and Puniſhments, the means ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God to teach people the knowledge and fear of God? or, <hi>Doth the Wrath of man accompliſh the Righteouſneſs of God?</hi> or, are theſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam</hi> 20.</note> the weapons of the Spiritual-Warfare, by which people are to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto the Lord in his Spiritual-Worſhip and Service? And is that Worſhip well-pleaſing or acceptable to God, which is forc'd only by the fear and puniſhment of men? or, doth God ſeek ſuch Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, as by carnal compulſion worſhip him? Nay, are not theſe of the weapons, with the which the many-headed Beaſt, with his Horns and Crowns, which riſe out of the Sea, have made War with the Saints for theſe many hundred years, and have ſo overcome them as to their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as that many have loſt their precious Lives in Priſons and Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, and at the Gibbet and the Stake?</p>
            <p>Was the material Temple by <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> to be rebuilt, without the help of Secular Force? and muſt there be the exerciſe of Inhumane Cruelty for the building of the Spiritual-Temple and Houſe of God, which in the Lord is the Pillar and Ground of Truth? Is not the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> now the builder of his Church? and is not He only given as a Leader, and the Commander of his People, in Spiritual things? for, is not all Power in Heaven and Earth, by his Father given unto him, for the eſtabliſhment of his Heavenly and Spiritual Kingdom and Government? and as the Lord of his own Houſe, is it not to be left to him, to order it and to govern it without the help of the force of man? for, is not the Spirit and Power of Chriſt, of more efficacy for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39442:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the government of his Church, than might and power by men? And how is God glorified in the Church by <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> throughout all ages <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.</note> world without end, if the Church be gathered and governed by the Authority and force of men? Is not the Law of God, which by his Spirit is written in the hearts of his People, and his Fear, and the Dread which by him is put upon them, the Covenant by which they are to draw near unto him, in his holy Worſhip, rather than the Laws and Penalties of men? And is not the Lords Covenant with his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the only force (that is to ſay, without the force of men) which by him is put upon them, as to his own Spiritual Service and Worſhip? And as to the Lord, is not his Covenant ſufficient, without the force of men? as it is written, <hi>As for me, this is my Covenant with them, ſaith the Lord; My Spirit which is upon thee, and my words which I have</hi> 
               <note place="margin">59.</note> 
               <hi>put in thy mouth, ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeed, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeeds ſeed, ſaith the Lord, from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, and for ever.</hi> And in the day of the Lord's Power, are not his People willing, without carnal compulſion by Secular force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence? And did not the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> (full of Power by the Spirit of the Lord, and of Judgment, and Might) declare againſt the Heads of the houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the Princes of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who built <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>c.</hi> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 10.</note> up <hi>Zion</hi> with blood, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with iniquity?</p>
            <p>And what remains now in this day of tryal for the <hi>Quakers,</hi> the true Succeſſors of the holy Prophets and Martyrs of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> but to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed them in their Sufferings, and fill up that which is behind of the Afflictions of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for his Bodies ſake, which is the Church? for, whilſt Laws are made and executed upon them, to limit them in their Meetings; by which they are made offenders, who otherwiſe are blameleſs; and whilſt their Meetings together in the fear of the Lord, and in obedience to his Law and Commandment, and in his Worſhip and Service, are rendred as the Tranſgreſſions of the Laws (they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the limited number of <hi>Four, &amp;c.)</hi> which otherwiſe and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that limit, are enjoyned by the Spirit of the Lord, and ſtrictly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired not to be forſaken by any, either wilfully after they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b.</hi> 10</note> the knowledge of the Truth; or for fear of Man, who when he hath killed the body can do no more, leſt greater ſufferings from God may be expected, to wit, a certain fearful looking for of Judgement, and the fiery Indignation of God; who can both kill the body, and caſt the ſoul into Hell; And what then now remains for the <hi>Quakers,</hi> in theſe exerciſes and tryals of their Faith and Patience, but to offer up their Bodies a living Sacrifice, holy and acceptable to God, as their reaſonable ſervice; and patiently to ſuffer all theſe cruelties, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39442:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
men may be permitted to inflict upon them? for, of neceſſity muſt they not either ſuffer, or flee their Teſtimony, and deny <hi>Chriſt</hi> before men, and expoſe him to open ſhame before his enemies, and them that hate his appearance, and that perſecute him in his members? And will not <hi>Chriſt</hi> deny them before his heavenly Father, that deny him before men? and will not <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhame them, when in the glory of his Father he is made manifeſt, who are aſhamed of him and of his Teſtimony, when in his members he is deſpiſed and perſecuted?</p>
            <p>And though the Meetings of the <hi>Quakers</hi> are by men rendred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, becauſe of the Laws that are made againſt them; yet, are they therefore ſinful in the ſight of God, or unlawful by the Law of God? or, are their Meetings therefore diſpleaſing to the Lord, becauſe they are envied and perſecuted by men? Would <hi>Daniel</hi>'s praying to his God have been the tranſgreſſion of a Law, if there had not been a Law made purpoſely againſt it? or, was his praying then, and his making ſupplications before the Lord, his ſin againſt the Lord, even then when there was a Law made againſt it, which they called a Royal Statute, and a firm Decree which altereth not? And although the Meetings of the <hi>Quakers</hi> are made tranſgreſſions before men, becauſe of the Laws that are made againſt them; yet, is it either a tranſgreſſion in it ſelf, or a ſin before the Lord, for innocent Lambs and the harmleſs Flock of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in obedience to the Voice of their Shepherd, to meet together and to be gathered in his Name (and he in the midſt of them, to feed them and to fold them) that they might be fed in his green Paſtures, and refreſhed with his living Fountains of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Life: Nay, was it not a tranſgreſſion in them among the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and their Apoſtacy and ſin againſt the Lord, who after they had received the knowledge of the Truth, did yet forſake the aſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of themſelves together, with them that perſevered in the Truth; <hi>And forſook not the aſſembling of themſelves together, but endured a great</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb</hi> 25, 33.</note> 
               <hi>fight of Afflictions, and were made a Gazing-ſtock both by Reproaches and Afflictions; and took joyfully the ſpoyling of their Goods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is not the Name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (which is above every name) even his Power and his Preſence, the Authority in which God's true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers are to gather together to worſhip him, rather than the Laws of men? for, is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> preſent in the midſt of them, who are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in his Name? are not God's true Worſhippers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to meet together in the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and by his Authority to worſhip God, as by the Spirit of <hi>Chriſt</hi> they are drawn and compelled, ordered and guided, which leads into all Truth, notwithſtanding the Laws of men? for wherein the Laws of men for Conſcience-ſake can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39442:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
be actively obeyed, are they not ſubmitted unto, and paſſively o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, yea and fulfilled, by their patient ſuffering of their penalties? And are not their Meetings lawful in the ſight of God, who are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in the Name of <hi>Christ?</hi> for, are they not owned of God by the Preſence of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the midſt of them? and do not they offer violence to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the midſt of them, who violate their Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that are gathered together in his Name? do not they diſpiſe him <note place="margin">10</note> who deſpiſe them? and, is not what is done to them for his ſake, by him eſteemed as done to him? And, were it not better for them, that <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 25. 5. 18.</note> a Milſtone were hanged about their necks, and they caſt into the Sea, than for them to offend one of the leaſt of his little ones?</p>
            <p>And, as to the place for Divine Worſhip and the Service of God, in the exerciſe of Religion; Are there now any certain places prefixt and limited unto by Chriſt, ſince the hour came that God would neither be worſhipped on the Mountain of <hi>Samaria,</hi> nor yet at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> are not all limits and ties to certain prefixt places for the Worſhip of God, made null and void by the Miniſtration of the Spirit and the Truth as it is in <hi>Jeſus?</hi> for, are not all diſtinctions of places by <hi>Chriſt</hi> annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, in that which to the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Woman, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4.</note> 
               <hi>me, the hour cometh when ye ſhall neither in this Mountain, nor yet at Jeruſalem worſhip the Father?</hi> And did not the then Teacher of the Gentiles, in Faith and Verity, will them <hi>to pray every where?</hi> aſwell <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> without any ſcruple to the place, as without doubting in what they asked according to the will of God? And doth not the Lord by the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> ſay, <hi>that IN EVERY Place Incenſe ſhall be offered unto his Name, and a pure Offering;</hi> and, <hi>that his Name ſhall be great among the Heathen?</hi> And in the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is it not ſaid, <hi>(viz.) It is very meet, right, and our bounden duty, that we ſhould at All times, and in All places, give thanks unto thee, O Lord Almighty, and everlaſting God, &amp;c.</hi> And is not Chriſt there, and in the midſt of them, whereſoever it be that two or three are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tth.</hi> 20.</note> in his Name?</p>
            <p>And, did not the primitive Chriſtians of the Cities of <hi>Corinth, Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> and <hi>Theſſalonica, &amp;c.</hi> in the Worſhip of God, meet apart from the Jewiſh Synagogues, and from the Idol Temples? And, were not the Aſſemblies of God's true Worſhippers in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> approved of by God, who in the Worſhip of God met apart from them who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in the Temple? for, were not the Churches of <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> and of all <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Macedonia,</hi> which were in God the Father, and in our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſo many diſtinct Congregations, and all ſeparated from their ſeveral National Worſhips? as in ſome Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39442:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the 2d <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 1. is read, <hi>Unto the Congregation of God which is at Corinth;</hi> and <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Unto the Congregations at Galatia, &amp;c.</hi> and as ſo many ſeparated and diſtinct Congregations, all in the Unity of God the Father and of Chriſt in the midſt of them; had not they pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authority from Chriſt, and by his Preſence with them, either in their own hired houſes, or in any other convenient places, to meet together in his Name, for the exerciſe of Religion and Worſhip, and the adminiſtration of holy things within and among themſelves.</p>
            <p>Are we not all to be the Servants of God only, and not the Servants of men, in the things of God, which concerns his heavenly Kingdom and Government? as it is written 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 23. <hi>Ye are bought with a price; be not ye the ſervants of men:</hi> for, are not the matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion God's matters? and, is not God only our Maſter in the matters of his Spiritual Worſhip? hath not the Lord only the ſole power over both our Souls and our Bodies, in his own Worſhip and Service? and is not the Lord only, the alone Judge in and over our Conſciences? And muſt not we all ſtand or fall to our own Maſter? as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 4. <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt another mans ſervant? to his own Maſter he ſtandeth or falleth.</hi> Is not mans judgment and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over the conſciences of the Lord's Servants, in the matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Worſhip, herein by the Apoſtle excluded, in that which he here ſaith, <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt another mans ſervant? to his own Maſter he ſtandeth or falleth.</hi> In the late <hi>Annotation,</hi> publiſhed in the year 1651, on <hi>John</hi> 7. 51. it is ſaid, <hi>Thoſe whom God hath ſet in Authority, may and ought to judge of Secular buſineſſes; but of mans final eſtate Chriſt only is to judge.</hi> And did not the Apoſtles deny Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip over the Conſciences of God's Heritage, and diſclaim to have any Dominion over their Faith? for, doth not <hi>Peter</hi> in his exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 3. 2 <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 24.</note> to the Elders to feed the flock of God, ſay, <hi>Neither as being Lords over God's Heritage?</hi> And doth not <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſay, <hi>Not for that we have Dominion over your Faith?</hi> Is there then any ſuch Lordſhip or Dominion, by the Secular Powers, in the Spiritual Body, as to give Law and Rule to the Faith and Conſciences of God's faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true Worſhippers, in the matters of Religion, and for the Worſhip of God?</p>
            <p>Are the Servants of God therefore to make men their Maſters in the Service of God? or, are the Commandments of men to be their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits and Preſcriptions for the Worſhip of God? or rather, Are not they falſe teachers, and themſelves in the falſe and vain worſhip, who for the Worſhip of God teach for Doctrines the Commandments of men? for, of ſuch worſhippers and Teachers doth not Chriſt ſay, <hi>But</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:39442:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>in vain do they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines the commandments of men?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th.</hi> 9.</note> And for the Servants of God, to reſign the power over their ſouls, and their ſoul-concernments, into the hands of men, and for them in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the commandments of men, to yeeld up the dominion over their conſciences to man, which only belongs to God; is not this in the things of God to make themſelves the Servants of men? and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is not the Lord rejected, and his Soveraignty and Dominion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and reproached? And in the concerns of their eternal being, do they not in this ſtand or fall to men, as their Maſters? or, will Chriſt profit them any thing, who in the things which concern his own Heavenly Kingdom and Government, do yeeld their Souls and their Conſciences to be yok'd and bound by men?</p>
            <p>Are not the Lord's Servants here (in the things of the Lord) both by the Apoſtles Doctrine and Example, to be left to their Lord's Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and to ſtand or fall, as by his Juſtice they are either juſtified or condemned, without their being judged by mans judgment? And as amongſt men, it is accounted unequal, for one man to exerciſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over another mans Servant, and an injury to the Maſter; So, doth not the Lord here by the Apoſtle ſharply reprove the preſumption of thoſe, who at all take upon them to judge the Lord's Servants in the matters of Religion; eſpecially in thoſe things which are owned <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> 18 7, 8, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> by him, and which by him are allowed in them; and wherein the Lord hath received them, and doth accept of them? And, will not the Lord as ſeverely judge them, and their uſurpation and Hypocriſie, as they in the exerciſe of authority over the Lord's Servants, are ſevere in their judgments, and do judge that which is of God in them: for, is it not an high provocation in them; and, are not they uſurpers, who exerciſe authority over the Servants of Chriſt, in thoſe things in which Chriſt only is their Lawgiver and their Judge? And, are not they hypocrites, who under the pretence of their ſervice to Chriſt, do perſecute the Members and Servants of Chriſt; and, that pretend it good ſervice to God, to make ſtrong the bands of the Righteous, and with the fiſt of wickedneſs to ſmite the Lord's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants? And when the Lord comes to make inquiſition for Blood, and wrongs done, in an hour that they are not aware of, will he not then remember them, and appoint them their portion with Hypocrites?</p>
            <p>For, as to the matters of Conſcience in Religion &amp; the Worſhip of God, and all thoſe things which relate to the inward man; is not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man to ſtand before the Judgement-Seat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his body? and is not this by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle made uſe of, as an Argument or Reaſon, why Chriſtians ſhould
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39442:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not therefore judge one another in the matters of Religion, nor ſet at nought their Brother, in things in which he is neither to himſelf nor to any man, but to the Lord only; in that which he ſaith, <hi>But why doſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10, 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>thou judge thy Brother? or, why doſt thou ſet at nought thy Brother? we ſhall all ſtand before the Judgment ſeat of Chriſt: For it is written, As I live, ſaith the Lord, Every knee ſhall bow to me, and every tongue ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to God.</hi> Doth not the Apoſtle herein, reprove among Chriſtians their judging one another, and their ſetting at nought one another in the matters of Religion, and all thoſe things in which they are to the Lord, and not to themſelves or to man, both as an uſurpation of Gods right, to whom only every knee muſt bow, and every tongue confeſs, as to all thoſe things which are only proper to the Judgment of God, and not to mans judgment? and alſo, as a violation of the Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; which relation of equality and fellowſhip as Brethren, in the things of God amongſt Chriſtians, and as Members together of the ſame Body, ſhould be preſerved in the unity of the Spirit and by the bond of Peace, and to defer them from it, by their being accountable to God for it?</p>
            <p>Are not the Lord's Servants in the things of God, which by Chriſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e diſtinguiſhed from the things that are <hi>Ceſars,</hi> therefore to be left it liberty by Magiſtrates, to ſtand or fall to their own Maſter; that is to ſay, as to their Conſciences in matters of Religion, and the Worſhip of God? For, in the regiment of their Souls, and the dominion over their Conſciences, is not the Lord only their Maſter, and not man? And, are they not therefore bought with a price, that in the things of God they ſhould not be the ſervants of men? And wherein they are Freemen, &amp; to be at liberty from the Laws of men; are they not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Lord's Servants, and under the Law to Chriſt? and even in the Body, are they not accountable to Him as their Judge, whoſe Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-ſeat is ſet up in their Souls? And by the Law of Chriſt are they not judged, if they tranſgreſs, in things in which rhey are at liberty from the Laws of men? for, doth not his Law take hold, where their Laws cannot reach? and, are not their thoughts, and the intents of their hearts opened in them, and manifeſt to the ſearcher of hearts? For, is not the Sword of his Spirit, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> his Word, which is nigh them, quick and powerful, and ſharper than any two-edged Sword, piercing even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, and of the joynts and marrow; to the deſcerning of the thoughts and intents of the heart? And is not the Judge of all (which either juſtifies or condems in every mans conſcience) alwayes before the door of their hearts, in their own conſciences, to condemn al that either entreth in or cometh forth, that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39442:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is againſt him? as it is written, <hi>Grudge not one againſt another, Brethren,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.</note> 
               <hi>leſt ye be condemned; behold, the Judge ſtandeth before the door.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in that which by the Apoſtle is concluded, as inevitable, viz. <hi>So then every one of us ſhall give an account of himſelf to God.</hi> Doth he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 14 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> not herein, reaſonably exclude the judgments of men, in the matters of Religion and Conſcience, relating to the Worſhip of God, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf next ſaith, viz. <hi>Let us not therefore judge one another any more; but</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 14 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>judge this rather, that no man put a ſtumbling-block, or an occaſion to fall in his Brothers way:</hi> for ſeeing that no man can by any means redeem his Brother, nor give to God a ranſom for his ſoul, but that every one muſt account for himſelf to God; is it therefore reaſonable, that any man ſhould impoſe upon another, contrary to his faith and conſcience, and in the ſpiritual concernments of his ſoul, relating to his everlaſting being, in which the Impoſer cannot anſwer to God ſatisfactorily for the impoſed upon, nor redeem his ſoul, he therein miſcarrying? And, do not they put ſtumbling-blocks in their Brothers way, and an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for him to fall, who impoſe upon their Brother in ſpiritual things, contrary to his faith and conſcience? for, <hi>whatſoever is not of faith, is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>ſin:</hi> and, <hi>if his own conſcience condemn him, God is greater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as every one muſt account for himſelf to God, is it <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn</hi> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> not therefore alſo reaſonable, that in the things of God every man's conſcience ſhould be thorowly ſatisfied, and their minds by the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> fully perſwaded; as it is written, <hi>Let every man be fully</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 14</note> 
               <hi>perſwaded in his own mind;</hi> rather than that any ſhould be forced con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their minds, and againſt their conſciences, by the laws of men: for, is not every one that doubteth in what he doth, condemned in himſelf? as it is written, <hi>He that doubteth is damned, if he eat.</hi> Doth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> 23.</note> it not therefore concern every one that believeth, to keep the Faith by which he ſtands, even as he hath received; and his conſcience void of offence; as it is written, <hi>Haſt thou Faith? have it to thy ſelf before</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>God. Happy is he that condemneth not himſelf in that thing he alloweth.</hi> And is not every mans conſcience to be perſwaded by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as ſaith the Apoſtle? <hi>I know and am perſwaded by the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and rather by the terrour of the Lord, than by the terrour of men; as it is written, <hi>Knowing therefore the terrour of the Lord, we</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 5</note> 
               <hi>perſwade men, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in order therefore to their being fully ſatisfied in their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences by the Lord Jeſus, are they not in the Light of Chriſt to try things that differ? and in all, are they not to prove what that good and perfect Will of God is? And when in the true diſcerning of that which is right in the ſight of God, they are fully perſwaded, and their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39442:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
conſciences thorowly ſatisfied by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; are they not ſtedfaſtly to hold faſt the Good, whatſoever Laws by men may be made againſt it; as it is written, <hi>Prove all things; hold faſt that which is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 5. 21</note> 
               <hi>good?</hi> for otherwiſe, if the matters of Faith, and the manner of Gods Worſhip, ſhould depend upon the Laws of men; may not then our Faith and Religion; and the manner of God's Worſhip, as oft be changed, as the minds of Magiſtrates may change?</p>
            <p>And, is it not poſſible that Magiſtrates may err in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Worſhip, (for therein are they not of different minds in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope?)</hi> and for the People to be ſeduced, even by their Magiſtrates? for of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> is it not ſaid, that <hi>he ſeduced the People to do more evil,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 21. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2 <hi>Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 12.</note> 
               <hi>than did the Nations whom the Lord deſtroyed before the children of Iſrael?</hi> And did not <hi>Jeroboam drive Iſrael from following the Lord, and make them ſin a great ſin?</hi> And doth not the Lord by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> as grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved therewith, ſay, <hi>O my People, they which lead thee, cauſe thee to err, and destroy the way of thy paths?</hi> And did not <hi>Judah</hi> quote to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> as examples, the Antiquity of their Anceſtors, and the Authority and Practice of her Rulers, for the abominable Idolatrous <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 17.</note> Worſhip; in the exerciſe of which ſhe promiſed to her ſelf both peace and plenty?</p>
            <p>And, were not the Idolatrous Prieſts ordained by the Kings of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Ki</hi> 23. 5</note> to burn Incenſe in the High-Places, in the Cities of <hi>Judah,</hi> and in the Places round about <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the true and Spiritual Worſhip of God, is there not the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe and operation of the true and living Faith, which worketh by Love? for, was it not by Faith that <hi>Abel</hi> offered a more acceptable Sacrifice than <hi>Cain?</hi> and, <hi>without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God: for he that approacheth to God, muſt believe that he is, and that he is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4, 6.</note> 
               <hi>of them that diligently ſeek him.</hi> And is this Faith either in the gift of Magiſtrates? or, doth it operate by the force of their Laws? And in order that the Lord may be truly, ſpiritually, and acceptably worſhipped; muſt there not be of neceſſity, an underſtanding in ſome meaſure of the Will of God in his Worſhippers; and ſo mixt with Faith, as that their minds may be fully perſwaded, and their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thorowly ſatisfied, both as to the matter and manner of his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? or elſe, will not their Sacrifice be as of the blind, and the halt, and maimed? And is this underſtanding of the Will of God given to them by the exerciſe of Secular-Force? or, are their conſciences to be ſatisfied by the executions of the Laws of men, and their Renal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? Or rather, are they not to <hi>look into the perfect Law of Liberty,</hi> (the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 25.</note> Royal Law, on which hangs all the Law and the Prophets; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39442:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to which the Laws of men ought to be regulated) which in their hearts is written, and not in litteral or outward Commands, nor by the Preſcriptions of men; but with the Spirit of the living God, and therein to learn of Chriſt the will of God concerning his own Worſhip and Service.</p>
            <p>And, muſt not the Lord be worſhipped by his own ſpiritual and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Birth, and with the returns of the breathings of his own Life, in the unity of his own Spirit, and of the Truth as it is in Jeſus; and rather according to the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, than either with the Inventions or by the Precepts of men? Or, can the Lord be truly and ſpiritually worſhipped on earth, but by his own Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and in the Truth, and of them that are of his Spirit? And, is the Spirit of the Lord either to be limited or directed by men? for, doth not the Prophet of the Lord ſay, <hi>Who hath directed the Spirit of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 40.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, or being his Counſellor, hath taught him?</hi> Or, do themſelves truly diſcern the Spiritual Worſhip of God, in the inward feeling of that which is Immortal of God in them, in which only God is to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped; and in the ſenſible motion and operation of the Spirit of God, ſpeaking in them, and making Interceſſion for them, according to the will of God, and not after the will of man; in which fleſh is to be ſilent, and the man paſſive, who preſcribes to others By Laws or Canons for the Worſhip of God? for, doth not the Apoſtle ſay, <hi>We</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 8.</note> 
               <hi>know not what to pray for as we ought, but the Spirit it ſelf maketh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt for us with ſighs which cannot be expreſſed?</hi> And, doth not Chriſt ſay, <hi>It is not ye that ſpeak, but the Spirit of your Father which ſpeaketh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>att. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>in you?</hi> And if the Apoſtles knew not beforehand what to pray for as they ought; is the Lord then truly and ſpiritually worſhipped by the reading of ſtinted Forms of Prayer, impoſed for the publick Worſhip of God, and which are not only known beforehand, but are alſo read week after week, and year after year?</p>
            <p>And if by might and power any ſhould be forc'd aſtray, to worſhip God in that manner which is contrary to the Law of God in their conſciences, (though highly eſteemed amongſt men) would not even their Prayers be their ſin? for, doth not <hi>Solomon</hi> ſay, <hi>He that turneth away his ear from hearing the Law, even his prayer ſhall be abomination. And he that cauſeth the Righteous to go aſtray by an evil way, ſhall fall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> 
               <hi>into his own pit.</hi> And is not their ſin great, and will not their ſtripes be many, who either by force or ſubtilty are either drawn or driven to worſhip God after that manner, which is contrary to their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and conſcience? And if by the force of Might and Power, any ſhould be driven contrary to God's witneſs in their conſciences, will
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39442:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they not hereby be run into tranſgreſſion and Rebellion againſt God? and will not the Witneſs of God in them, in their own conſciences, be their condemnation? And is not Rebellion as the ſin of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, and Tranſgreſſion as Wickedneſs &amp; Idolatry? And, are their own conſciences pure and without offence, and tender, and in the feeling of anothers conſcience? or rather, are not their conſciences repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, without remorſe and unſenſible, who by force would defile and offend, and even wound and wrack the conſciences of others?</p>
            <p>And do not they ſin againſt Chriſt the Head, who ſo ſin againſt his Body the Church, and who grieve his Spirit, and oppreſs his Members, by impoſing rigorouſly upon them heavy burdens, which they are not able to bear, even to the wounding of their conſciences if they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; and, as much as in them lyeth, to deſtroy their ſouls for whom Chriſt died? And if the doubtful thoughts of them that are weak in the Faith, in things that are lawful in themſelves, are not to be judged; as it is written, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 1. <hi>Him that is weak in the Faith, receive you, but not to judg his doubtful thoughts,</hi> (ſee the margent.) Is the faith and certain knowledge of God's true Worſhippers then to be judged as to the manner of God's Worſhip, which they aſſuredly believe to be the will of God, and certainly know to be of the Lord, and required of them, as his Law unto them? Was the noiſe either of Hammer or Ax, or of any Tool of Iron, heard in the Houſe of God whilſt it was in building by <hi>Solomon?</hi> And are the Laws of men then, and their Penalties and Puniſhments, to be the Foundations now, on which God's Spiritual Houſe is to be built? or, is the matter for the Houſe of God now, to be hewen out, and hammered, and prepared by armed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and the noiſe of the clattering of Arms, with which the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Meetings of the <hi>Quakers</hi> have been often aſſaulted and broken up, and their Bodies hurt and bruiſed? Is Force and Violence ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed by men on the Body, the way of God to ſave the ſoul? Did not the Prophet in the power of God, and in the might of his Spirit, declare againſt them, who built up <hi>Zion</hi> with blood and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> with wrong?</p>
            <p>And is it not uncharitable among Chriſtians, and againſt the Law both of Love and Equity, and that which they would not be done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelves; for one to impoſe upon another, as to their Faith and Conſcience, in the matters of Religion and Worſhip, contrary to the Law which rules in their Conſciences, and to that which they believe to be the Will of God; and to that in which they are not to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but to the Lord; and to that in which the Lord hath received them, and doth accept of them? For, doth not the Royal Law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39442:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>to love thy neighbour as thy ſelf?</hi> and hath not Chriſt to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 2.</note> commanded, ſaying, <hi>Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, do ye even ſo to them; for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>att.</hi> 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Are not even Gainſayers by ſound Doctrine, both to be convinced and exhorted? and in meekneſs are not they to be inſtructed, who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves? and are not even unbelievers, and them that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to be gathered by the Word of God preached, and to be won by moderation and ſoberneſs, and by the good converſation of them that believe? And is not the Word of God of more force, inwardly to execute the righteous Judgments of God for diſobedience, and to convince, perſwade, and compel to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, than all the force and ſtrength of men? for, is it not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the Lord likened to a Fire, and to a Hammer which breaks the Rocks in pieces? reader <hi>Ier.</hi> 23. 29. &amp; 20. 9. &amp; 6. 11. &amp; 5. 14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 2. &amp; 30. 30. &amp; 11. 4.</p>
            <p>And, was not the Baptiſm of Repentance, which by <hi>Iohn</hi> was preached, as an <hi>Ax</hi> from God in his hand, for the cutting down of fruitleſs Trees? and were not they prickt in their hearts with the force of the Word, and the authority of the Doctrine, which by the Apoſtles was preached? And did not <hi>Foelix</hi> tremble before <hi>Paul,</hi> when he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned of Righteouſneſs, and Temperance, and of Judgment to come? And is not therefore the matter for the building of the Church of God, to be prepared by the Miniſtry of his Word in God's Authority, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than by the force and terror of men? And are not even thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, to be ſubdued by the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt</hi> unto the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of God, in his Spiritual Service and Worſhip? For, is not the Goſpel of Chriſt the Power of God? And, is not the Authority of the Word, and the Force of the Goſpel, in which the Power of God is made manifeſt, the means by God appointed to ſatisfie doubts; and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide Controverſies in matters of Religion and manner of Worſhip? For, is not the Word of God both quick and powerful, and the Sword of the Spirit, and ſharper for the convincement of Gainſayers, than the two-edged Swords of men? for, doth it not pierce, to the diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the thoughts and intents of the heart, and inwardly force and compel, where the Force of men can neither reach nor enter?</p>
            <p>And if Power in Magiſtrates over the Faith and Conſciences of God's faithful and true Worſhippers in the matters of Religion and Worſhip, be pretended unto as they are Magiſtrates; may not then Antichriſtian or Heathen Magiſtrates, pretend to the ſame power, to over-rule the Faith of their Subjects, and compel them to their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and by their penalties and puniſhments, to force their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39442:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to worſhip Idols? And, if ſuch power in Magiſtrates be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended unto as they are Chriſtians; are we not to diſtinguiſh between the Office or Authority of Magiſtrates, in the adminiſtration of their Civil Power, as Rulers and Governours; and the Religion of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates as they are Chriſtians; by which they have fellowſhip in the Church, as Members of the Spiritual Body; of which Chriſt only is the Head; among them that in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> are called &amp; ſanctified through the Truth, in which many are one Body, and all Members one of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; and all partakers of one Bread, and all made to drink into one Spirit? And as Chriſtians therefore, are not all Brethren, as in that ſtate, and the Chiefeſt to be the Servant of all, and that not ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tularly only, and be ſerved of all, but in the Truth and for the Goſpel-ſake to ſerve all?</p>
            <p>And whereas thoſe Scriptures, viz. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 13. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1 <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2. 3</note> 
               <hi>higher Powers, &amp;c.</hi> and, <hi>Put them in mind to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers, to obey Magiſtrates, &amp;c.</hi> and, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, &amp;c.</hi> are many times, by many brought againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> thereby to ſignifie to them, as if ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and obedience to Magiſtrates, as to their Faith and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in the matters of Religion and the Worſhip of God, is required of them by the authority of theſe Scriptures.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, That in theſe Scriptures precited, here is indeed requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſubjection and obedience, even by Chriſtians to Magiſtrates, in all thoſe matters and things which concern their outward man; but, that ſubjection and obedience to Magiſtrates by Chriſtians, as to the exerciſe of their Faith and Conſciences, in the matters of Religion and the Worſhip of God, which are the concerns of the inward man, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reaſonably be underſtood here, to be required by the Apoſtles in theſe Scriptures. I offer this as reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe the then Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, to whom obedience was required by the Apoſtles, as to Religion were Heathens, and worſhippers of falſe gods; And is it reaſonable for any to believe, that the Apoſtles herein, required that the primitive Chriſtians ſhould ſubject the exerciſe of their Faith and Conſciences, under the dominion of them, that as to their Religion were Infidels; or, that the Church of Chriſt, as to matters of Religion and the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, ſhould be governed by Heathen Rulers, that were them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Idolators and worſhippers of falſe gods?</p>
            <p>And if it ſhould be yet aſſerted by any, That the Apoſtles here in theſe Scriptures, intended the ſubjection and obedience of the inward man; and that the primitive Chriſtians were to be ſubject as to their Faith and Conſciences, in the matters of Religion and the Worſhip of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39442:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
God, to the then Heathen Magiſtrates; will it not then follow, that if the then Heathen Magiſtrates had made Laws to force the primitive Chriſtians from their Chriſtian Religion, and their Worſhip which is in Spirit and in Truth, according to the Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 4. And to require them to worſhip the falſe gods of the Heathen <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the Idols which the then Heathen Magiſtrates worſhipped; Muſt not the primitive Chriſtians then of neceſſity have been ſubject? And is not this abſurd to aſſert? And muſt it not therefore of neceſſity fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that the ſubjection and obedience here required by the Apoſtles in theſe Scriptures, is only as to all thoſe matters and things which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the outward man; and not at all of the ſubjection of the inward man in the things of God, which relate to his own Spiritual Worſhip and Service?</p>
            <p>And as to this diſtinction, did not Chriſt himſelf diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween things; and aſcribe to God his things <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the things that are proper to God only, and not to man; and alſo, allow unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> his things <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to the chief Magiſtrates of every Nation, the things that belong to them, in that which he ſaith, <hi>Render therefore to Ceſar the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atth.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 21.</note> 
               <hi>things that are Ceſars, and unto God the things that are Gods?</hi> And is not the inward man the Image of God? and are not the things of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, which relate to the Worſhip of God, of his inſcription, or under his only Dominion; as <hi>Caeſar</hi> had his image and ſuperſcription ſtampt on their Coin, to ſignifie his Dominion over them, as to the things of their outward man? And in that which <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man, &amp;c.</hi> is it not manifeſt, that he herein intended their ſubmiſſion in the things of the outward man, by his own example in the caſe; for when the Magiſtrates interpoſed their Commands in the things of God, did he not anſwer them, ſaying, <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God, to hearken unto you more than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cts</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>God, judge ye?</hi> And again, did not he, with the other Apoſtles, in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Magiſtrates, ſay, <hi>We ought to obey God rather than men?</hi> And <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cts</hi> 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> was it not as to the matters of Religion, and for the exerciſe of their Faith and Conſciences in the Service and Worſhip of God, that the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians ſuffered Perſecution by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates?</p>
            <p>And whereas, when things by Magiſtrates are commanded, which for Conſcience-ſake cannot be obeyed by them who endeavour to keep their Conſciences void of offence, that which is written, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 5. <hi>[Wherefore ye muſt needs be ſubject, not only for wrath, but alſo for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence-ſake]</hi> is often objected, thereby to inſinuate, That Magiſtrates have dominion over the Conſcience in the things of the inward man.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:39442:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>I anſwer,</hi> That every man is bound in his Conſcience by the Lord and to the Lord, to obey the juſt Commands of their Magiſtrates, not only for wraths ſake by man, but alſo for conſcience ſake to God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Scripture, is not at all by the <hi>Quakers</hi> denied; But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Magiſtrates are to be obeyed for conſcience ſake to God; and as the conſcience is bound by God to their obedience, and not by man, doth it therefore follow that Magiſtrates have dominion over the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? And are not Magiſtrates as wel to be ſubmitted unto for the Lord's ſake, as for conſcience ſake? or, have Magiſtrates dominion over that in others, which in themſelves hath dominion over them? For, is not that in man called <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which in the light of Chriſt both knows and feels; and which as it were is the Throne of God in man, and the Seat of his divine Law, and of the Juſtice of God? for hath not every man either peace or trouble, as with the Light of Chriſt (which is the Law of God) in his own conſcience, he is either juſtified or condemned?</p>
            <p>Or, can Magiſtrates be obeyed for conſcience ſake in things againſt conſcience? or, can they be ſubmitted unto for the Lord's ſake in things againſt the Lord? or, muſt Magiſtrates be obeyed for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake in the things of the outward man; and muſt not the Lord be obeyed for conſcience ſake in things of the inward man, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns his own Worſhip and Service? or, do they either obey God or Magiſtrates for conſcience ſake, who in the Worſhip of God are by men forc'd againſt their conſciences? And becauſe Magiſtrates are by Chriſtians to be obeyed for conſcience ſake, may it not therefore be of caution to Magiſtrates in their Government, to take heed, that they require nothing againſt the Law of God in the conſcience, that ſo by Chriſtians they may be obeyed for conſcience ſake? And if the Laws of men do anſwer to the Law of God in the conſcience, will not every one then that reſiſts the Power, as well be made ſenſible of the wrath of God in his conſcience, as deſerving of the wrath of men upon his outward man?</p>
            <p>And by the oppoſite Commands of God and man; are not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of them that are required to obey, deeply concerned, and themſelves greatly tryed? for of neceſſity are not they forc'd into ſore ſufferings, either by the wrath of God, or by the wrath of man; that is to ſay, if man forbids that which God commands, or if God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids that which man commands, muſt they not ſuffer either by God or man? for in this caſe of neceſſity muſt not either God or man be diſobeyed? And if they obey the Laws of men, contrary to the Law of God; do they not then incur the wrath of God? and if they obey
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39442:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Law of God, contrary to the Laws of men; do they not then incur the wrath of men? And although the Wrath of God be the greater; yet, is not the wrath of men very great, and grievous to be born, when it is executed?</p>
            <p>But in this caſe, muſt not the Lord be obeyed rather than man? For, as to Soveraignty, is not the Lord higher than the higheſt? and, doth not the Lord regard the Oppreſſions of the Innocent; who in their ſufferings have none to flee unto but to himſelf only? as it is written, <hi>If thou ſeeſt the Oppreſſion of the Poor, and violent perverting</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leſ.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>of Judgment and Juſtice in a Province, marvel not at the matter: for He that is higher than the Higheſt regardeth; and there be higher than they.</hi> And, doth not the wrath of man turn to the praiſe of God? <hi>And the remainder of wrath will not he reſtrain?</hi> And, as to their eternal eſtate, Are not the concerns of the ſoul, greater than the concerns of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? and, even in this life, is not peace with God in the conſcience, more to be regarded, than to be parted with to avoid ſufferings by men? For, what is any man profited, by eaſe, liberty and pleaſures in the body, if to gain this, he loſe his ſoul? and what would not a wiſe man part with, or ſuffer, to gain his ſoul?</p>
            <p>And, are not Magiſtrates as they are Chriſtians, prohibited by <hi>Chriſt</hi> from the exerciſe of authority and dominion over the Faith and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of God's true Worſhippers, in the matters of Religion and the Worſhip of God; as it is written, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. 25, 26, 27. <hi>The Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe dominion over them, and they that are great, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe authority upon them: but it ſhall not be ſo among you; but whoſoever will be Great among you, let him be your Miniſter: and whoſoever will be Chief among you, let him be your Servant.</hi> Which cannot be underſtood, that Chriſtians ſhould not be ſubject to the juſt Government of their Chriſtian Magiſtrates in Secular things; becauſe in Secular things, even Chriſtians are bound in conſcience by God, to be ſubject to the juſt Government even of Heathen Magiſtrates; May not this prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, viz. <hi>But it ſhall not be ſo among you,</hi> therefore be rather un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, the prohibiting by Chriſt of Secular Authority and worldly Dominion, to be exerciſed among Chriſtians, for the government of his Church in the Heavenly and Spiritual things of God? And alſo, becauſe in the Government of the Church, <hi>The Greateſt is to be their</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 44.</note> 
               <hi>Miniſter, and the Chiefeſt to be the Servant of all:</hi> and is it ſo in the Government of the Church by Secular Powers?</p>
            <p>For, is not the Church of Chriſt, a Spiritual Body? and muſt not its Government therefore be Spiritual, even by the Divine Authority and Heavenly Dominion of Chriſt himſelf, as the alone Head and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39442:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Governor of the Church, which is his Myſtical Body, and the fulneſs of him that filleth all in all; And may not this therfore be of caution, as well to Chriſtian Magiſtrates, as to Heathen Magiſtrates, to take heed of exerciſing that Authority and Dominion among Chriſtians, over the Spiritual Body of Chriſt, in the matters of Faith and Worſhip, and the things of God relating to the inward man; (which by Chriſt are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, from the things of <hi>Ceſar)</hi> which they exerciſe, and which may be given them of God, to be exerciſed by them, for their Civil Policy, and the Government of the Politick Body, in things Secular and relating to the outward man? For, is not the Power by which the Church is to be governed, by the Father given to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the only Head of the Church? and hath not <hi>Chriſt</hi> in himſelf kept the right of Soveraignty in the Government of his Church? and is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ever preſent in Spirit with his Church, for the adminiſtration of his Authority and Supremacy over the Church, and in the exerciſe of his Soveraignty for the Government of the Church? And, doth not <hi>Chriſt</hi> inſtruct them, and rule among them, by his Word and holy Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and his Commands unto them, and by the operation of his Power in them? and doth he not teach and govern them by the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and miniſtries, and conduct of his Spirit, which abideth with them, and dwelleth in them; and by the vertues and efficacy of the gifts of his Grace, which by him are diſtributed to them? And herein doth not <hi>Chriſt</hi> reign, and rule, and teach and govern his Church him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? and hereby is not God glorified in the Church by <hi>Chriſt</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ages? as it is written, <hi>Unto him be glory in the Church, by Chriſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſus, thorowout all ages, world without end. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though Authority, and Superiority, and Magiſtracy, and Power juſtly derived, and lawful Dominion, in the exerciſe of Civil Power, for the Government of the Politick Body, be the Ordinance of God; yet doth it therefore follow, that the ſame is ordained of God for the Government of his Church? For, are the motions of the Spirit of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Church, and the operations of the Power of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his <hi>Myſtical Body,</hi> by Magiſtrates to be bounded and limited, through the exerciſe of their Dominion over them, and of their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity upon them; Are the gifts which by God are given, for the mutual edifying of the Church, to be ordered and diſpoſed of by Magiſtrates? have they power over, and the government of the manifeſtations of the Spirit of God, and all thoſe different Adminiſtrations, which are by the ſame Lord, and which by the working of one and the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, operateth ſeverally in all, for the benefit of the Body, and the profit of every member? Or, had the then Heathen Magiſtrates the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39442:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſame Authority over the Power and Spirit which operated in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and primitive <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as they were the Miniſters and Servants of God, in the exerciſe of their Miniſtry and Service of the Church, which they had over their perſons, for obedience to their juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands in outward things relating to their outward man? or, have Chriſtian Magiſtrates now the ſame dominion over the Spiritual Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations of holy things in the Church, by the members of the Church, or by thoſe who by the holy Ghoſt are made Overſeers, to feed the Church of God, which they have over their perſons, for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their juſt commands, in outward things, relating to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man?</p>
            <p>For, are Secular Laws and Penalties, the means appointed by God, to make Diſciples for Chriſt; or, being made, to regulate them in the Spiritual Service and Worſhip of God? can the outward force of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal compulſion by pains and puniſhments, ever truly convert to God, or make clean the heart, or regenerate the ſoul, or renew a right ſpirit in man? And muſt not that regulate, in the ſpiritual Service and Worſhip of God, which begets, and converts to God? Nor is that which Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 23. <hi>Compel them to come in,</hi> to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of Secular force or outward compulſion, but of the force of the Goſpel of Chriſt; which is the Power of God to Salvation, and the compelling vertue of the Spirit of Chriſt; which in the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, by anſwering the witneſs in the conſcience, reacheth to the ſpirit in priſon, and by a taſte, not only invites, but by its power and vertue, compels and draws to the Lord's Supper, them that were ſcattered by their extravagant luſts; nor did the Apoſtles in their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Warfare, war after the fleſh, or by the help of humane force, or outward compulſion; <hi>For the weapons of their Warfare were not Carnal,</hi> or by Secular Laws and Penalties; <hi>but mighty through God, to the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down the ſtrong holds,</hi> of them that ſtrengthened themſelves againſt the knowledge of God; <hi>and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt;</hi> neither did they revenge the diſobedience of any, in matters of Worſhip, by the hand of the Magiſtrate, inflicting pains and puniſhments on the body; <hi>for they wreſtled not againſt fleſh and blood, but againſt powers of darkneſs,</hi> and the ſpirits of wickedneſs, which ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hold the creature, under the dominion of Sin, and the reign of the Devil.</p>
            <p>And to them that reſtrain this prohibition of Chriſt, viz. <hi>But it ſhall not be ſo among you,</hi> as if Chriſt herein only prohibited the exerciſe of Heatheniſh Tyranny and Oppreſſion among Chriſtians; I ſay, what Tyranny and Oppreſſion is greater, than by might and power to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39442:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Faith of the Juſt, and to oppreſs their Conſciences? And if Heathen Magiſtrates, becauſe of their power and greatneſs, may not after their own wills and pleaſures domineer and over-rule among Heathens, in the things of the outward man; may Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates then, by their power and might over-rule and domineer over Chriſtians in the things of the inward man, and which relate to the Spiritual Service and Worſhip of God?</p>
            <p>And if a quiet and peaceable life, in the exerciſe of all Godlineſs towards the Lord, and in his Worſhip and Service; and of all Honeſty amongſt men, in their common occaſions, was the right of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> from their then <hi>Heathen Magiſtrates,</hi> though in the moſt material and weighty matters of Religion and Worſhip they differed from them; why may it not be much rather the right of <hi>Christians</hi> now, from their profeſſed <hi>Christian Magistrates,</hi> without being moleſted by them, to live quietly and peaceably, in the exerciſe of all Godlineſs and Honeſty, though they differ as to the manner of Worſhip; they giving unto Magiſtrates the things that are theirs, and unto God the things that are God's; which Right, that it might be enjoyed by the Lord's People, they by the Apoſtle are exhorted, <hi>That</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1, 2</note> 
               <hi>Supplications, and Prayers, and Interceſſions, and giving of Thanks be made for all men; for Kings, and all that are in Authority: that</hi> both <hi>they may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all Godlineſs and Honeſty;</hi> that their Magiſtrates alſo may have <hi>the knowledge of the Truth,</hi> and their <hi>ſouls ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when, through the Propheſyings of the Prophets, <hi>Haggai</hi> and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ez<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 1,</note> 
               <hi>Zecharia,</hi> by the commandment of God, the Jews again began to build the Houſe of God; and though <hi>Darius</hi> the King, as to the Religion and Worſhip of the Jews, was a Heathen, yet he did not hinder them, nor at all moleſt them; but rather furthered them by his aſſiſtance and protection; and alſo furniſht them with Sacrifices, to the end, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ez<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 6, 9,</note> they might pray for the Life of the King, and for his Sons; and that Wrath from God might not break forth againſt the Realm, the King and his Sons? And did not <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> in his Decree, ſubmit the concernments of the Houſe of God, to the Commands of God, in that which he ſaith, <hi>Ezra</hi> 7. 23. <hi>Whatſoever is commanded by the God of Heaven, let it be diligently done, for the Houſe of the God of Heaven: for why ſhould there be wrath againſt the Realm of the King, and his Sons?</hi> which latter clauſe by ſome is read, <hi>the Realm, the King, and his Sons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas the examples of <hi>Cyrus, Darius,</hi> and <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> Kings of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and reputed Heathens, are by ſome brought, (as having au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39442:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
over the Jews, as to the building of their Temple, and as regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating and reforming them as to their Sacrifices and Worſhip) as Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to prove, That <hi>Chriſtians</hi> now are to be ſubject to their <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrates</hi> in the matters of Religion; that is to ſay, as to their Faith and Conſciences in the Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>To which <hi>I anſwer,</hi> firſt as to <hi>Cyrus;</hi> What Commands did he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon the Jews, as to the matters of their Religion; or what force did he put upon them, as to the building of the Temple? was not the ſum of his Proclamation, for Liberty to the captive Jews to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to their own Land, and there to build the Temple? And was not this in their advantage, and as they would have it, as to their Liberty, and to worſhip God, as God himſelf had commanded them; and might not who would, go, and who would, ſtay? And were not their ſpirits raiſed up by the Lord, without the force of man, who to build the Houſe of the Lord, went up with the chief of the Fathers of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and the Prieſts, and the Levites, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 1. 5. And was not the ſpirit of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> alſo, (as to this thing) ſtirred up by the Lord, that the Word of the Lord, by the mouth of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> might be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? And though <hi>Cyrus,</hi> as to other things, perhaps may be reputed as a Heathen; yet may this therefore be reputed as heatheniſh, which was of the Lord, and who long before he was born, was by the Lord, called <hi>his ſhepherd? Iſa.</hi> 44. 28. And although <hi>Darius</hi> the king, as to Religion and Worſhip, differed much from the <hi>Jews,</hi> yet herein, was he not an example of moderation and of indulgence, as to their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, therein, (who were then under his Dominion, as to their outward man) rather than of exerciſing Authority over them, as to their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and manner of Worſhip; in that he was not provoked to anger againſt them, nor at all diſpleaſed with them, for their enterprizing the building of the Temple, without either his Command for it, or knowledge of it; and for that they deſiſted not from building, though they thereunto were required, (till the matter was made known to the King) by the chief Governours for the King on that ſide the River? And what reaſon is here then, for any to quote the example of <hi>Darius,</hi> as if he exerciſed authority over the Jews as to their building the Temple; and as if they could not righteouſly enterprize it without Command from the King being firſt had for it, ſeeing that when they began to build, they were ſo far from having the Kings Command for it; as that the King knew not of it, till by his Governours he was informed of it, and that the work went faſt on, and proſpered in their hands; and alſo, ſeeing that the Governours for the King could not cauſe them to ceaſe but till the matter came to the King, that from the King they might know his pleaſure therein?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:39442:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And after the Interruption, by the force and power of the former <hi>Artaxerxes, Ezra</hi> 4. 23. and in the Reign of this <hi>Darius,</hi> is it not manifeſt by the Scriptures, that the <hi>Jews</hi> again began to build the Temple, by the Command of God only, through the Propheſying of the Prophets <hi>Haggai</hi> and <hi>Zecharia, Ezra</hi> 5. 12. <hi>Hag.</hi> 1: 1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 8, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.1</note> 12. And was not the ſpirit of <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> (the Governour of <hi>Judah)</hi> and the ſpirit of <hi>Joſhua</hi> the High Prieſt, and the ſpirit of all the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the People, by the Lord ſtirred up, to work in the Houſe of the Lord of Hoſts, their God, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. 14. And in that, they could not be cauſed to ceaſe but till the matter came to the King, did they herein diſobey the Governours for the King, in contempt to his Government? or rather, was it not becauſe the eye of their God was upon them? <hi>Ezr.</hi> 5. 5. for, did not they begin their work in obedience to the voice of the Lord their God, and continue it in the fear of the Lord, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. 12. and was not the Lord's preſence with them in their work, as in that which is written, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. 13. <hi>I am with you, ſaith the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when the matter, to wit, of their building the Temple, was made known to the King, by Letter to him ſent to that end, from his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours that were on that ſide the River, did the King at all render the Jews as diſaffected to his Government, or diſobedient to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, or inconſiſtent with his Laws? or did anger at all kindle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him againſt them, for their enterprizing the building without his knowledge of it, or commiſſion for it? or, in his Decree, did he at all intermeddle with them in their building, (either by his Commands to his Governours, or by his own Commands to them) except thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of his to his Governours, to aſſiſt the Jews out of his Goods as to their great expence in building, that they might not be hindred in their work; and for Sacrifices to be given them day by day, that by ſweet ſavours offered to the God of Heaven, they might pray for the life of the King, and for the lives of his Sons, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. 8, 9, 10. for in the King's anſwer to the Governours that ſent to him, did not the King command the Governours, not at all to meddle with the Jews in the building of the Temple, but to let them alone, that in peace they might build the Temple themſelves, in that which to them he ſaith, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. 6, 7. <hi>Be ye far from them: let the work of this Houſe of God alone, let the Governour of the Jews, and the Elders of the Jews build this Houſe of God in his place.</hi> And did not the King by his Decree alſo protect them, and ſtrengthen their hands, and inforce it by a great penalty? and what in him lay, did he not promote the continuance of their Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by his Succeſſors, rather than to exerciſe authority over them, as to the Temple and Worſhip of God? as you may reade in <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. 11, 12.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:39442:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And was not this alſo of the Lord, (who turneth the hearts of Kings as he pleaſeth) and not of the Heatheniſh nature, as it is written <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. 22. <hi>For the Lord had made them joyful, and turned the heart of the King of Aſſyria unto them, to ſtrengthen their hands in the work of the Houſe of God, the God of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Temple being finiſhed, in the ſixth year of the Reign of <hi>Darius</hi> the King, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. 15. the Worſhip of God in his Reign was ſo eſtabliſhed, according to the Commandment of God, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. 16-22. as that here ſeems to be no need of a Reformation, as to the Worſhip of God, by <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his Succeſſor, who by ſome is quoted, for the Reformation of the Church; And if in any thing, the Church was not perfectly reformed as to the Worſhip of God, might not the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God as well be reformed by the Commandments of God, in the Reign of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> as they by the Commandment of God began to build the Temple, in the Reign of <hi>Darius,</hi> without either his Commiſſion for it, or knowledge of it? May not the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefore, by <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> (the latter) mentioned in <hi>Ezra</hi> 7. ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther relate to the Civil Government of the Province of <hi>Judah,</hi> which as yet was not reformed according to the Law of God, than to the Worſhip of God, in his Temple? for when the <hi>Jews</hi> were not in Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, but as free-men at liberty in their own Land, were they not by the Ordinance of God, both to be governed by Magiſtrates that knew the Law of God, and alſo according to the Law, which by God was given to <hi>Moſes</hi> for their Government? And to that end, had not <hi>Ezra</hi> prepared his heart, both to ſeek the Law of the Lord, and to teach in <hi>Iſrael</hi> Statutes and Judgments? <hi>Ezra</hi> 7. 10.</p>
            <p>And was not the hand of the Lord upon <hi>Ezra,</hi> as well for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Civil Government in <hi>Judah</hi> according to the Law of God, as for another return of the <hi>Jews</hi> to their own Land, when <hi>Ezra</hi> made requeſt to <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> the King, who granted him all his requeſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the hand of the Lord his God upon him, <hi>Ezra</hi> 7. 6. for to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the King's Commiſſion, to <hi>Ezra</hi> given, for all the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Prieſts and Levites that were within his Realm, to go with <hi>Ezra,</hi> that were minded of their own free-will to go up to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> was not <hi>Ezra,</hi> as the King's Commiſſioner, ſent by Authority of the King, and of his ſeven Counſellors, to enquire concerning <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> according to the Law of God; And over all the Land of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to ſettle Magiſtrates, and Judges, that knew the Laws of God, and to teach them that knew them not; And by the Kings Commiſſion, was not power to him given for their execution of the Law of God, and the King's Decree, upon Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:39442:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
either unto Death or to Baniſhment, or to Confiſcation of goods or to Impriſonment, that ſo the people all might be judged, and gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, even as to their outward man, according to the Law of God, and by Magiſtrates, and Judges, that knew the Law of God?</p>
            <p>And as to that, which perhaps, by ſome may be alledged to prove Reformation as to the Worſhip of God, by <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> the King, viz. that both <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> the King and his Counſellers offered freely, and bountifully, of their Silver, and Gold, and that the King gave power, to <hi>Ezra</hi> for Collections in the Province of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and for the freewil Offerings of the People, and the Prieſts, and therewith, to buy Bullocks, and Ramms, and Lambs, &amp;c. for Sacrifices; and with his Brethren, to diſpoſe of the reſt, after the will of God, and as to what might farther be needful, for the Houſe of God, that he ordered <hi>Ezra,</hi> to beſtow out of his Treaſure-houſe, and that he made a Decree for his Treaſurers, to give unto <hi>Ezra,</hi> Silver, and Wheat, and Wine, and Oyl, and Salt, to a great value, if by <hi>Ezra</hi> it ſhould be required of them?</p>
            <p>To which I ſay, are they not to diſtinguiſh, between the exerciſe of Authority, for the correcting, altering, or preſcribing, as to the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and the exerciſe of Authority, for the encouragment, and protection of God's true Worſhippers, in the Worſhip of God, as by God himſelf it is preſcribed and reformed? And did not <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> the King, herein, like a Nurſing-father, even to the Church (though otherwiſe reputed a Heathen) exerciſe his Imperial and Kingly Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, for the encouragement and protection of the Jews, in the Worſhip of God, as by God himſelf it was preſcribed and reformed, rather than that he intruded his own Authority or Commands, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the Church, as to the Worſhip of God in his holy Temple? for, as to all things which related to the Worſhip of God in his Temple, did not <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> the King ſubmit the ſole Government and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10, 12.</note> of the Church, to God himſelf; yea, and that with fear and reverence to God, as a <hi>conſuming fire;</hi> leſt by the Wrath of God, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with his Realm and his Sons, ſhould be conſumed; in that which he ſaith, <hi>Ezra</hi> 7. 23. <hi>Whatſoever is commanded by the God of Heaven, let it be diligently done for the Houſe of the God of Heaven: for why ſhould there be wrath againſt the Realm, the King, and his Sons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And hereby, is not their error made manifeſt, or their malice, or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the Scriptures, who in their Pulpits, before the Judges, do make uſe of that which in <hi>Ezra</hi> 7. 26. is written; <hi>Whoſoever will not do the Law of thy God, and the Law of the King, let judgment be ſpeedily executed upon him; whether it be unto Death, or to Baniſhment, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation of Goods, or to Impriſonment;</hi> with endeavour to incenſe the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:39442:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Judges, to exerciſe cruelty, upon the innocent, by their miſinterpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and wrong application, when the <hi>Quakers</hi> are to be tryed upon the Act for Baniſhment, or Impriſonment, for their meeting together in the fear of the Lord, and in his Name, to worſhip him; And herein do they not wreſt the Scriptures, to oppreſs the Innocent, that are more righteous than themſelves?</p>
            <p>And if by the judgments and executions, of the Law of God and the Law of the King, and the penalties and puniſhments in this Scripture mentioned, here was intended by the King, a compulſion, as to the matters of Religion, and a force, as to the Worſhip of God, in order to a uniformity, in Religion and Worſhip, among all thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, over whom the Magiſtrates and Judges, by the Kings decree, were to be ſetled, as in the Wiſdom of God, <hi>Ezra</hi> ſhould be guided to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect; muſt not all the people then have been forc'd as to their Religion and their Worſhip, by thoſe penalties and puniſhments, that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the River; in which were ſeveral Provinces? or at leaſt, ſhould not all the people then, by theſe judgments and executions have been compelled to be one with the <hi>Jews,</hi> as to their Religion; and with them to have worſhipped in the Temple, that were in the Province of <hi>Judah</hi> or in the Cities of <hi>Samaria, &amp;c.</hi> in which there were of ſeveral Nations, and they of ſeveral Religions, and ſeveral manners of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; for is not that which in this Scripture is ſaid, <hi>Whoſoever will not do the Law of thy God, and the Law of the King, &amp;c.</hi> intended of all the people that were beyond the River, as in the verſe before, and as much as to ſay, Whoſoever of all the people that are beyond the River, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And was Judgement ever ſo executed upon this people, to force them as to their Religion, and the ſeveral manners of the Worſhip of each Nation, in which every Nation worſhipped their own gods? or, were the ſeveral Nations, mentioned <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. 9, 10. ever compelled by thoſe penalties and puniſhments, to be of the <hi>Jews</hi> Religion, or with them to worſhip in the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> Nay, would not this rather have gratified, the Nations, who in thoſe Countries were the <hi>Jews</hi> adverſaries, then the Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who publickly could have worſhipped with the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Temple, and alſo privatly have ſerved their own gods? for when the <hi>Jews</hi> laid the foundation of the Temple, would not they have builded with them? and did not they ſeem to inforce, the accompliſhment of their deſire therein, by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of unity with them, in that which to <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> and to the chief of the Fathers, they ſaid, viz. <hi>Let us build with you; for we ſeek your</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. 2.</note> 
               <hi>God,</hi> as ye do, and we do ſacrifice unto him, &amp;c. And did not the <hi>Jews</hi> both deny them, and account the Temple profaned, by the preſence of profane men in it, and alſo both their worſhip, and themſelves defiled
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39442:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by their fellowſhip with Idolaters in it? And muſt not then thoſe penalties and puniſhments, have been executed, cheifly on the <hi>Jews,</hi> if the ſpeedy execution of Judgment, ſpoken of in this Scripture, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to the ſetling of a uniformity in Religion and Worſhip, among all thoſe People and Nations, over whom thoſe Magiſtrates and Judges were to be ſetled; And then would not the <hi>Jews</hi> have been the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſufferers, in whoſe favour the Decree by the King was intended and granted? for if they choſe rather not to build the Temple, than to admit of them to build with them; could they at all communicate with them in the Worſhip of God, who no otherwiſe feared the Lord, but as every Nation alſo ſerved their own gods.</p>
            <p>Again; Are not the penalties and puniſhments, that are mentioned in this Scripture, <hi>viz. unto Death, or to Baniſhment, &amp;c.</hi> both the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Executions of the Law of God, and alſo Secular penalties and puniſhments? and doth the Law of God compel any of his true worſhipers, to worſhip him by the force of Secular penalties &amp; puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? or, is that worſhip acceptable to God which is by compulſion and force? And to that which perhaps by ſome may be ſaid, That the penalties and puniſhments herein mentioned, are the judgments and executions of the Law of the King. I ſay, are God's true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, by the Laws and Preſcriptions of men, to worſhip God after that manner which is contrary to that which by the Law of God is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for his Worſhip? or, are they by penalties and puniſhments to be forc'd as to the Worſhip of God, contrary to their Faith, and to what they believe to be the true Worſhip of God, and againſt their Conſciences? And, was not the Law of God then, the Law of the King alſo, when the King by his Decree had eſtabliſhed it, as his Law, to be adminiſtred in their Judicature?</p>
            <p>Is not therefore that part of the King's Decree, which in <hi>Ezra.</hi> 7. 25, 26. is contained, intended by the King, of the exerciſe of his Civil Power, for his reforming of the Magiſtracy and outward Judicature in the Province of <hi>Judah,</hi> for the Civil Government of the Jews, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of God, as to their outward man, as in the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God <hi>Ezra</hi> ſhould be guided to direct it; and not for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of the Church as to the Worſhip of God: for as to what in his Decree, related to the Houſe of God and his Worſhip, and to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters thereof, did not his Decree end (as to the before-mentioned) with the end of the 24th verſe of that chapter? or, did the King at all reform the Church, as to the Worſhip of God, otherwiſe than as by his Decree he ſubmitted the reformation of it to the Commandments of God himſelf, and by his ordering that to be diligently done for the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39442:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Houſe of the God of Heaven, which either was or ſhould be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the God of Heaven, as in ver. 23. and alſo as by his Decree he protected the Jews in the free exerciſe of their Liberty, as to their Conſciences, in their obedience to the Commands of God, as to his own Worſhip and Service.</p>
            <p>And as to that which perhaps by ſome may be objected, That theſe penalties and puniſhments may be executed, as to the matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Worſhip, becauſe the Law of God is as well there menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned as the Law of the King, viz. <hi>Whoſoever will not do the Law of thy God, and the Law of the King, &amp;c.</hi> To which I anſwer. Was not the Law of God, by the Law of the King eſtabliſhed, to be adminiſtred in the outward Government of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as to the things of their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, and to be executed upon Offenders in their Civil Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, according to the nature and degree of each tranſgreſſion, as by the judgement of the Judicature they were ſentenced, whether unto Death, or to Baniſhment, or to Confiſcation of Goods or Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for, were not the Jews in their liberty from Captivity, to be judged and governed according to the Law of God, even as to the things of the outward man, and by Magiſtrates and Judges that knew the Law of God? And were not the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> therefore to have <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut.</hi> 17. 19, 20</note> a Book of the Law of God, and therein to read all the dayes of their lives; that they might learn the fear of the Lord their God, and keep the words of his Law, and his Statutes, to do them; and that their hearts might not be lifted up above their Brethren, nor they turn aſide from the Command of God neither to the right-hand nor to the left.</p>
            <p>And, in order to the adminiſtration and execution of the Law of God in their Civil Judicature, was not <hi>Ezra</hi> therefore, after the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, as his guide, by the King's Decree to ſettle Magiſtrates and Judges that knew the Law of God, and to teach them that knew it not; for, had not <hi>Ezra</hi> prepared his heart to ſeek the Law of the Lord, to do it, and to teach in <hi>Iſrael</hi> Statutes and Judgments? And, did not the King direct his Commiſſion to <hi>Ezra,</hi> as to a Scribe of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra</hi> 7. 11, 12.</note> Law of God, and a Teacher of the words of the Commandments of God, and of his Statutes to <hi>Iſrael?</hi> And do not Statutes there relate to State-Government and Civil Judicature? And was not <hi>Ezra,</hi> by the King and his ſeven Counſellors, ſent to enquire concerning <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> according to the Law of his God? were not therefore theſe penalties and puniſhments (in the adminiſtration of the Law of God, by Magiſtrates and Judges which knew the Law of God) to be executed upon malefactors for their capital or criminal offences againſt the Law of God, rather than upon Innocent and regular people, for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:39442:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the exerciſe of their Faith and Conſciences to God in his Worſhip and Service?</p>
            <p>And may not theſe penalties and puniſhments be annexed by the King, to inforce his Decree, and accordingly to be executed upon any of the Jews adverſaries, that at any time ſhould oppoſe this his new Conſtitution of the Magiſtracy for the Government of the Jews, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of God? for had not the <hi>Jews</hi> many potent Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries nigh them, who waited opportunities to miſchieve them? as in the caſe of the building of the Temple, were not many exaſperated againſt the Jews, leſt by it their Idolatrous High-Places ſhould be clouded? So in time, might not their potent Adverſaries be exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated at this new Reformation of the Magiſtracy, for their Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, according to the Law of God, in which they had not the ſame opportunity, as Lords of their own Rule, to tyrannize over the Jews as formerly?</p>
            <p>And withall, may not theſe executions, viz. <hi>unto Death, or to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, or to Confiſcation of Goods, or to Impriſonment;</hi> the rather be thus particularly ſignified and expreſſed, thereby to demonſtrate the greatneſs of their Authority by the King's Commiſſion, for the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Law of God in their Civil Government, and the ample Power which by the King's Decree was given them, for the execution of Judgement in their Judicature, as to the things of the outward man? Which Power here thus largely extended, was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards denied them by the <hi>Romans;</hi> when under their Dominion, it was not lawful for the Jews to put any man to death, <hi>Iohn</hi> 18. 31.</p>
            <p>And as to that which in this kind is objected by ſome of the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> viz. <hi>That they exerciſed Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the matters of Religion, &amp;c. and that therefore Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates may now, yea and that they ought, ſo to exerciſe their Power and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over Chriſtians, as even to force and compel them, as to the maner of the Worſhip of God; though it be contrary to their Faith and againſt their Conſciences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, firſt; Do not the Statutes of ſeveral Kingdoms in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> differ, as to the matters of Religion, and their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and form of Worſhip? and have not the Laws for Religion and Worſhip at ſundry times differed, even in this our own Nation, as the Magiſtrates, or thoſe in power, by which they have been made, have differed in their minds as to their Religion and Worſhip? And if the matters of Religion, and the manner of the Worſhip of God, ſhould be only directed and governed by the Laws and Statutes of men; May there not then be as many Religions and forms of Worſhip, or as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:39442:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
changes in Religion and Worſhip, as the Magiſtrates that differ ſhould pleaſe to make?</p>
            <p>And if <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are bound actively to ſubmit to the Laws of their <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrates,</hi> as to their Religion and Worſhip, without any further queſtion, though againſt their conſciences; why then have ſo many Martyrs ſuffered Martyrdom for their not ſubmitting (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than by ſuffering) to the Laws for Religion and Worſhip, which have been made by them, who in their times have been called <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrates?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as to all the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which reigned after the diviſion of the ten Tribes from the Kingdom of <hi>Iudah,</hi> what Authority they exerciſed in the matters of Religion, was it not to ſupport their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Worſhip, which by the ſubtilty and craft of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> was both invented and ſetled as the Publick Worſhip of the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. 12. 27, 28</note> And to promote Idolatry in Worſhip, and againſt the Law of God, were not the Statutes of <hi>Omri</hi> both added and kept, who walked in the way of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and in his ſin, wherewith he made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin? And <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> as if it had been a light thing to walk in the ſin of <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> did not <hi>Ahab</hi> worſhip <hi>Baal,</hi> and rear up an Altar for <hi>Baal,</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Baal</hi> which he built in <hi>Samaria?</hi> And is it not ſignified by the Prophet <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah,</hi> as the peoples ſin againſt the Lord, that the <hi>Statutes of Omri were</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ah 6.</note> 
               <hi>by them kept, and all the works of the houſe of Ahab, and that they walked in their counſels?</hi> And in point of Worſhip, was not the Lord provoked to anger, by the obedience of the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to the Heatheniſh Statutes of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which they had made, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17. 8. And would their alledging their Kings Laws, as their Authority for what they did, at all have excuſed them before the Lord, or pacified his Anger againſt them for it? And was not their ſin great, who by <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng. 21.</note> force were driven from following the Lord, to worſhip at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel?</hi> And, was not <hi>Ephraim</hi> oppreſſed and broken in judgement, becauſe he willingly walked after the Commandment? And by the <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 5. 11.</note> Captivity of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> did not the Lord remove them out of his ſight, as well for their perſiſting in the ſins of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> even until their Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, as alſo for their other Idolatries in Worſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> their walking <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 23.</note> in the <hi>Statutes of the Heathen</hi> (whom the Lord caſt out from before them) <hi>and of the Kings of Iſrael, which they had made?</hi> And even in the time of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Apoſtacy, were there not many of the Lords People, that for Conſcience ſake could not keep the <hi>Statutes of Omri,</hi> nor the <hi>works of the houſe of Ahab;</hi> and that walked not in the heatheniſh Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which they had made, as witneſs the ſeven thouſand in the time of <hi>Elias, that never bowed their knee to Baal?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:39442:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And if as Kings, the Commands of any of the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> were abſolute, and to be over the Conſcience in the matters of Worſhip; were not then the Commands of them all, as Kings, abſolute, and to be over the Conſcience in the matters of Worſhip? And if the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were bound in Conſcience, as in the matters of Worſhip, actively to ſubmit to their Commands, though againſt their Conſciences, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further queſtion as to right or wrong; who of them could then eſcape from being Idolaters, that lived under the Reign of the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Princes? for in the Cities of <hi>Judah,</hi> and round about <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> were there not High-Places in their ſeveral ſtreets, and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto ſeveral ſervices; ſome of them for the worſhip of falſe gods, and others of them for the Worſhip of the true God, but all contrary to the Law of God, as it is written, <hi>Wo, wo unto thee, ſaith the Lord,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eze<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 23, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>that thou haſt alſo built unto thee an eminent place, and haſt made thee an high-place in every ſtreet; thou haſt built thy high-place at every head of the way, &amp;c.</hi> And were not the Idolatrous Prieſts, that burnt Incenſe in the High-Places, ordained by the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> which afterwards by <hi>Joſiah</hi> were put down, as it is written, <hi>And he put down the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Prieſts, whom the Kings of</hi> Judah <hi>had ordained to burn Incenſe in the High-Places in the Cities of</hi> Judah, <hi>and in the places round about</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And did not the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> as to the matters of Worſhip, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter their Power differently, as they were diverſly affected; for, as there were ſome that took away the Altars of the ſtrange gods, and deſtroyed their High-places, and that brake down their Images, and cut down their Groves; ſo, were there not others that built High-places, and ſet up Images, and that reared up Altars to <hi>Baalim,</hi> and made Groves, and that walked in the wayes of the houſe of <hi>Ahab?</hi> As there were ſome who did that which was righteous in the ſight of the Lord, by their reforming the abuſes of their fore-fathers, as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Joſiah</hi> and others; ſo, were there not others who did that which was evil in the ſight of the Lord, and more eſpecially, as to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion and Worſhip, and that walked in the wayes of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as <hi>Jehoram, Ahaziah</hi> and others? And did not the Lord bring <hi>Judah</hi> low, for the ſake of <hi>Ahaz</hi> their King, who tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſorely againſt the Lord? for, did not <hi>Ahaz</hi> make <hi>Judah naked?</hi> which by ſome is read, <hi>he withdrew in Judah the Worſhip of God.</hi> And, <note place="margin">2 Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 28. 24, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> when he had <hi>ſhut the doors of the Houſe of the Lord;</hi> did he not <hi>make him Altars in every corner of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and High-places in every ſeveral City of</hi> Judah? And of <hi>Jehoram</hi> is it not ſaid, That <hi>he made High-places</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 11, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>in the Mountains of</hi> Judah, <hi>and cauſed the Inhabitants of</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:39442:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>to commit Fornication, and compelled</hi> Judah <hi>thereto.</hi> And of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 21. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on</note> is it not ſaid, That <hi>he made</hi> Judah <hi>to ſin with his Idols, and the Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to err? and that he ſeduced them to more evil than did the Nations, whom the Lord deſtroyed before the children of Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And even among the good Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> though <hi>Aſa</hi> and <hi>Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> took away the Altars of the ſtrange gods, and brake down their High-places, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet by them were there not left ſtanding other high-places, which by the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould have been demoliſhed? and <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 43.</note> is it not recorded as their remiſneſs, that they were not by them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed? Howbeit they forc'd none, no not to ſacrifice to the true God, in the high-places, but ſuffered it in thoſe that did. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Jehoaſh, Amaziah, Azariah</hi> and <hi>Jotham,</hi> did many things that were right in the ſight of the Lord; yet, did not they all leave ſtanding the high-places? and under their Reigns and Government, did not the people ſtill ſacrifice and burn Incenſe in the high-places, which by the Law of God was not lawful for them to do, but in the Temple only?</p>
            <p>And as to the courage and fidelity of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and the zeal and piety of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and their more thorow Reformation, ſo much ſpoken of; to wit, their throwing down the high-places, as well thoſe, which by the former Reformers were left ſtanding, as thoſe which after were built; and their breaking down the Altars, and caſting out the Images; and their countenancing the true Worſhippers, and encouraging the Worſhip of God, according to the Law and Covenant of God: all which, as aforeſaid, is objected by ſome, as examples for Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates to follow, and for them therefore to exerciſe their Authority as to matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer. If the Lord put it into the hearts of Chriſtian Magiſtrates, ſo far to tread in the ſteps of the good Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> as to encourage the true Worſhip of God, which is in Spirit and in Truth, and not after the inventions of men; and to protect God's true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers in their Worſhip of God, and to exerciſe their Authority for the removing the heaps of high-places in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were built either by pattern or Command from God, and for the demoliſhing of their eminent places, with their Altars within them; and Popiſh Images about them, who of the Lord's People would be grieved therewith? for which reade 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. 3, 4. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23. &amp; 18. 4. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. 14. <hi>Numb.</hi> 33. 52. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. 5. &amp; 12. 2, 3. And, as before it is obſerved, Was it not recorded as the remiſneſs of the former good Kings of <hi>Judah, That the High-places were not removed, though in them the people ſacrificed to the true God only?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:39442:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
But did thoſe good Magiſtrates and Reformers in the Church and Commonwealth of <hi>Judah,</hi> at all preſcribe to God his Worſhip? or, did they adminiſter their Power, for the execution of their own wills, concerning the Worſhip of God? Was not their Authority by them exerciſed for the eſtabliſhment of the Law of God, and his Ordinances for his Wolſhip and Service, according as by <hi>Moſes</hi> was declared and written before them; and for the keeping of God's Teſtimonies, which by God was teſtified in his Spirit by his Prophets, and in their own conſciences? For, did not <hi>Ioſiah</hi> make a Covenant before the Lord, <hi>To walk after the Lord, and to keep his Commandments, and his Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 34. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>and his Statutes, with all his heart, and with all his ſoul, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the words of the Covenant, which were written in the Book that was found in the Houſe of the Lord?</hi> And of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> is it not ſaid, <hi>That</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>he clave to the Lord, and departed not from following him, but kept his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, which the Lord commanded Moſes?</hi> And of <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> is it <note place="margin">2 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> not ſaid, <hi>That he ſought to the Lord God of his Father, and walked in his Commandments, and not after the doings of Iſrael?</hi> And when <hi>Aſa</hi> had taken away the Altars of the ſtrange gods, and the High-places, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> did not he <hi>command Iudah,</hi> or rather, as it is in ſome Tranſlation, <hi>he</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 14. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſaid unto Iudah, that they ſhould ſeek the Lord God of their Fathers, and do after the Law and Commandments?</hi> And was not the uprightneſs of their hearts ſuch, as to the Lord, his Law and Commands, to them in what they did, as that their Commands by the people were obeyed as the words and Commandments of God? as it is written, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 29. 15. <hi>And they gathered their Brethren, and ſanctified themſelves, and came ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Commandment of the Kings by the words of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> for they in their Commands obeying the Word of the Lord, the Hand of the Lord was ſo upon the people, as that they obeyed their Commands as the Word of the Lord; as it is written, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 30. 12. <hi>Alſo in</hi> Judah <hi>the Hand of God was to give them one heart to do the Commandment of the King, and of the Princes, by the Word of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to conclude, both as to Chriſtian Magiſtrates, and alſo as to Heathen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates; If Heathen Magiſtrates command Chriſtians, even in the matters of Religion; the Commandments of the Lord only, and not their own, againſt their Lords; are they not even by Chriſtians to be ſubmitted unto for the Lords ſake? And if Chriſtian Magiſtrates command Chriſtians, even as to the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, the Commandments of Chriſt anſwering to the Witneſs of Chriſt in their conſciences that are to obey, and not by carnal compulſion, or the force of man, againſt their Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h and Conſciences, are they not by Chriſtians to be obeyed, yea, and even for Conſcience ſake? But if the Commands of Magiſtrates (whet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er as to their profeſſion they be either Heathens of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) be contrary to the Commands of God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Faith and Conſciences of Gods faithful and true Worſhippers, in this caſe, is not the Lord rather to be obeyed than Men?</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
